The state's architectural pattern is probably one of the most important patterns in software architecture.
In fact, if I had to single out one pattern as the one you must implement, it probably will be the
Stickles pattern.
So what is this little thing?
Instead is architecture.
The application state is told in only two places, the data store and the user interface, if there
is any.
No state is told in the application code.
Now, if you are not sure what state is, you can think of it simply as the applications data is a temporary
or persistent to make it clearer.
Let's use an example in our example.
Our application has a look in mechanism similar to almost any other application out there.
The application consists of user interface, login service and a database.
The user enters his username and password.
They are sent to the lock in service, which checks with the database whether such a user exists.
If so, the user data is retrieved from the database and are stored in a variable in the service so
that in future requests the application will be able to identify him.
In this example, the state which in this case the user details, is stored in the application code,
thus making it stateful rather than stateless.
Now, what is the problem with why you stateful called considered a bad thing?
To understand that, we should discuss two other concepts that we already mentioned before but are worth
mentioning again.
The first is scalability.
As you probably remember, scalability is a capability of the system to grow and shrink as needed when
there is a peak in the load of the system is scalable system can simply add more resources and we are
not needed anymore.
These resources are removed.
All this without any interruption to the systems activity.
As you probably remember, we discussed the difference between scale up and scale out and concluded
that scaling out is almost always preferred over scaling up.
The second concept is redundancy.
Redundancy means that when resource of the system stops functioning is because of a system problem or
because of a hardware glitch.
The system will continue functioning using additional identical resources it has and can also perform
automatic scaling to other resources instead of the malfunctioning resource, for example, with a system
with more than one server.
If one of our servers experiences electricity problems and shuts down, the system will be able to continue
functioning with additional servers and perhaps even create a new server and add it to the existing
ones.
Those two concepts are the cornerstone of any good architecture and must be taken into account when
designing the system now to implement its concept.
Architecture must look like this.
As you can see, we have more than one service instance, the exact number doesn't really matter, but
the best practice is to use at least three instances in front of the service.
There is a load balancing the robot and there is an appliance or a software that has two roles in the
architecture.
First, it distributes the load between the servers.
If one of the servers is very busy, the balance will you out requests to another server.
It will make sure no server will crash under the load.
This capability supports the scalability we need using the robot until we can add more servers as needed
and just notify the balance of the new servers.
Second, it checks for the status of the servers enough to stop routing requests to malfunctioning ones.
The way it works is that the load balancing center periodically requests to its servers called is a
requests and expects to get a response with a positive answer.
Any other response or no response at all will indicate there is a problem with the server and they will
stop routing requests to the server.
As you can see, the strong support, the redundancy we talked about, the robot also allows the application
to continue walking even if one or more of the servers are down.
This is exactly what we want to achieve with redundancy.
There are a lot of balancing algorithms, but the basics are always the same.
Distribute the load and stop routing to nonfunctioning servers.
OK, so we have learned about scalability, redundancy and load balances, but what does it have to
do with Tetris architecture?
Well, actually, these are tied to each other.
Stateful node status application will have a very hard time with scalability and redundancy.
Lizzi Way.
Remember the Logan scenario, let's look at it again, but now from a point of view of a full blown
system with multiple servers and a load balancing, so the user logs in the quest containing the username
and password is sent and reaches the load balancer, which routed to server number one.
The server performs the login process and keeps a variable for verifying the user in future requests.
Now the user performs another request.
Let's say he wants to add item to a shopping cart.
The request containing the item to be added is sent which to the.
But this time the balance allows it to server number two.
Now look what happens.
The request arrives at several Oberto, but this server has no idea who the user is.
The data containing the user data is on server number one.
What will happen in this case is that the user will get an error message saying he should log into the
system, which will leave him confused since he just did exactly that.
And the one thing you don't want to do to your users is to confuse the.
The reason for that, Evo, is that the court is stateful, the application code contains state or data,
which is the user details in this case, additional resources or servers that are used for scalability
or redundancy simply have no idea about the data in the code and behaves as if it does not exist.
The state fullness of the code makes the application harder to scale and damage the user experience.
Now, what would have happened in a stateless architecture in this case as user data will be saved in
some kind of data store?
It could be a relational database and logical database, a distributed cache, anything that can be
accessed from all the servers.
Then when the request arrives to the server, it could release the data stored for the user details
and immediately knows exactly who the user is, regardless of the server that performs the actual login.
Note that this goes the same for redundancy.
If the server that performs login was shut down for whatever reason, subsequent request would be routed
to it.
And again, the server accepting the request will have no idea who the user is.
So this is the reason why this architecture is so important.
It fully supports scalability and redundancy, which make your application much more reliable.
To conclude, always make you architecture stateless, there are almost no scenarios which justifies
stateful architecture and you probably will never encounter them.
This is the best way to support scalability and redundancy in your system, and you should definitely
use it.