Caching is one of the most used architectural patterns in software, but is not always used correctly.
Let's explain the basic concept of caching first.
Using cache, we bring data closer to its consumer so that its retrieval will be faster.
Let's look at some examples.
All the modern web browsers have cache.
The role of the cache in web browser is simple when browsing a specific web page, instead of asking
a remote server to serve the page, it is retrieved from the browser's memory, thus displaying the
page much faster.
The developers can disable the cache to ensure the page displayed is always up to date and contains
the relevant data.
Let's look at another example more relevant for us the architects.
A service needs data from the data store.
Let's assume the data store is a relational database like SQL Server.
Naturally, the service has code in its data access layer to access the database and issue SQL statements
to retrieve the data.
The retrieval operation can take some time.
The database has to compile the SQL statement, retrieve the data.
Then the code will need to serialize the data to objects.
The code can work with.
All this might take time.
Add to that the fact that the database might be physically located far from the code, and we do have
an inefficient process.
To avoid this delay, we can use cache.
The cache is another layer usually sits between the data store and the business logic layer that stores
data in a way that makes it very easy and fast to retrieve.
Cache engines usually store data in memory, thus making the retrieval extremely fast.
Some engines, such as Redis, save the data to disk periodically, but still retrieving the data is
done against a memory storage.
Cache engines offer some trade offs when compared to more traditional databases.
The following table summarizes this tradeoff.
As you can see, cache trades reliability for performance.
Data stored in memory is more volatile and will be lost in case of a server crash.
On the other hand, it is more performant compared to traditional databases because databases usually
store the data in disk.
We almost always will refer to them as the single source of truth, meaning the real original data is
stored in the database.
And if the data is missing from the cache, we will fall back to the database to retrieve it.
Now, as architects, we must be able to determine whether when and how to use cache in our system.
And for that, let's first define the type of data that we would want to cache.
The rule of thumb goes like this.
Cache should hold data that is frequently accessed and rarely modified.
The reasoning behind this rule is simple.
If data is frequently accessed, we would like to make it fast and easy to retrieve so that the user
experience will be optimized and there will be minimal load on the system.
By placing the data in the cache, we get just that.
The retrieval process is very lightweight since the data is in memory and no i o operation required.
And as a result it's also very fast making the user experience optimized.
On the other hand, the data should rarely be modified.
The reason for that is this.
One of the greatest challenges with cache is keeping it in sync with the data store, which is our single
source of truth.
If the data store and the cache are not synchronized and contain different data, it can lead to data
corruption and bad user experience.
Again, let's look at an example.
Our application gets stock quotes data and displays it to the user to make things quick.
The data is stored in the cache.
Now, naturally, stokes data changes quite frequently.
Let's assume the data changes each second.
Most of the users work with the stock quotes data right in front of them so they can see the numbers
change in real time.
This complies to the frequent access part of our rule.
Now what happens when the data is changed, which happens each second, Remember?
Let's assume the system complies with the architectural pattern we discussed previously, which means
we have three servers with load balancer in front of them.
Note that every server has its own cache.
Let's assume the servers expose API to update the stock quote and new call to the API arrives and the
load balancer decides to route it to server number one.
It gets the data, updates the central database and also updates its own cache.
And here is a problem.
Zarkesh on the other servers contains stale data.
That is a data that is not relevant.
The other caches were not updated as a result of the API call.
So now two servers hold data that is not up to date and not relevant.
And when the user will ask for the stock quotes and the load balancer will route the request to one
of these servers, the user will be presented with a wrong data, which is bad.
So what can be done?
To understand the various solutions?
Let's categorize the various types of cache.
In general, we can say there are two types of cache in memory, in process cache and distributed cache
in memory.
In process is a cache implementation that is part of the services code.
It uses the service memory and is executed as part of the services process.
Almost all the development languages have libraries for in-memory, in-process cache and actually for
simple implementations, you can use static concurrent collection and call it a day as you can probably
guess, in memory cache excels in performance, since accessing it is as simple as calling a class in
the code which gets data from the process memory.
On the other hand, it is limited in size since it can hold data as big as a process memory which is
usually a few gigabytes.
Distributed cache is a completely different beast.
It's a separate product that holds the cache data in a separate process and provides easy interface
for accessing the data.
The best part of the distributed cache is that it's well distributed.
That means that the cache storage is distributed across servers and that gives the distributed cache
the ability to store very large data.
In fact, the cache size is limited only by the combined memory size of all the servers.
The distributed cache is installed on distributed cache engines are usually installed as services on
the servers they are on and each service is called Node.
What's nice with distributed cache engines is that the nodes are synchronized internally and it's the
responsibility of the cache mechanism to make sure all the nodes are familiar with new data.
So in this case, when a specific server updates the cache, it's immediately distributed to the other
nodes, allowing all other servers to be in sync and have the same data.
So what is the downside of distributed cache?
The answer is performance.
While with in-memory in-process cache, the performance is blazing fast because the cache executes in
the same process and uses the same code with distributed cache.
We don't have this advantage.
The cache runs on a different process and sometimes it even runs on different servers, which adds network
hops to the retrieval process.
In addition, most of the distributed cache engines allow storing only primitive types, strings, numbers,
etcetera, while the in-memory in-process cache can store anything.
This gives us another performance gain since there is no need to serialize and deserialize the data.
And now let's go back to our rule cache.
Should hold data that is frequently accessed and rarely modified.
And we left in the middle of the rarely modified discussion.
If the data is frequently modified, as is the case with stock quotes and we are using in-memory in-process
cache, we will have to develop some mechanism to sync between the data in the database and each and
every in-memory cache.
This mechanism will hammer the database constantly and we will lose.
One of the advantages of cache, reduce the load from the system.
On the other hand, if we will be using distributed cache, we will probably be fine.
The updated data will immediately sync between all the nodes and the servers will access the fresh data.
So we explored in-memory in process cache versus distributed cache.
Let's summarize it all in the following table, which will help you decide what kind of cache you need
to use.
So use distributed cache if you need distribution among servers, failover capabilities and large cache
storage and use in-memory in-process cache if you need best performance possible.
And store complex objects.
In addition, using distributed cache requires some training and setup, whereas in memory, in-process
cache is as simple as using a class.
So that concludes our discussion about cache.
I hope you learned from it and I hope it will help you design your caching strategy in the future.