In this section, we talked about system architecture and the main aspects of it.
Using the concepts we have learned in this section, wisely, you will be able to design system architecture
that ensures your system is fast, secure, reliable and easy to maintain.
Note that it's extremely important to make the right choices as early as possible.
Many concepts we have discussed in this section are difficult to change once made.
For example, moving from rest API based messaging to queue based messaging will result in a rewrite
of at least some of the components of the system.
So always try to make sure your decisions are as informed as possible.
Also, note these concepts are not exclusive.
Of course there are more decisions that must be factored in and of course there are a lot more of work
to do than to choose the right logging and monitoring and to select the right messaging method.
But the concepts discussed here are usually the most important ones and you will find yourself using
them in almost every system you will design.