Those of you remember the first Shrek movie, probably remember the layers in Shrek tries to explain
to Donkey that ogres like every other living creature have layers and they are not one dimensional evil
creatures.
This is one of the funniest scenes in the movie, and it makes me laugh every time I watch it and I
watch it a lot.
And it also holds true for software architecture because a good software component, just like evil
ogres, will always have layers.
The role of the layer, though, is quite different in software than in monsters.
The layers in software component represent the horizontal functionality of the code in the layers.
Now what does it mean?
Traditionally, software components perform three basic actions.
One, expose the software functionality through some kind of interface.
This is usually done via API or user interface.
Depends on the type of the application to execute logic on the data that is received from the user.
Again via API or user interface.
This logic often includes validation processing, additional calculations, enrichment and more.
And three Save the data into the data store and retrieve data from the data store.
Now these three actions are usually represented as layers when every layer has its own name in software
components architecture.
These layers are called user interface or UI.
If the component has user interface or service interface or see if the component exposes API business
logic or BLE and data access layer or dull.
Each layer consists of various classes that handles the layers designated task.
For example, the dull layer will have classes that handle opening connection to the data store, querying
data saving data handling transactions and more.
The layer will have classes that performs validation, enrichment and computations.
The C layer will have classes that exposes API, translate Json documents to concrete objects, handle
authentication and authorization and more.
Now you might be asking what is the purpose of the layer?
Why would I want to separate the code to these layers?
Well, there are some very good reasons for that.
First, it forces you to write code that is well formed and focused.
It's generally a bad idea to write a method that performs multiple tasks, and we will discuss it later
in this section.
And by splitting the code to well defined layers, the code will deal only with its layers goal.
Second layer component is a modular component.
As you might recall, we discussed modularity as one of the most important quality attribute of a software,
and by implementing layers our component becomes just this modular.
Assuming the communication between the layer is done correctly.
And we will touch on this in a minute.
It's extremely easy to substitute layers.
For example, if the current implementation works against SQL Server and you want to switch to MongoDB
in a well layered component, you will only need to replace the dull layer and no other layers will
be affected, which makes your code really modular.
In order to develop a good layered architecture, there are some concepts that must be followed.
One code flow, which means a layer can call only a layer that is directly beneath it in the code.
What this means is that, for example, the code in the C layer can call only a code in the B layer,
never a code in the dull layer.
In addition, a code can never call a code in a layer above it.
For example, the dull code will never call a code in the blue layer.
The idea here is to keep the separation between the layers as strict as possible.
If you will enable skipping layers, that will mean that the C layer, for example, knows about the
dull layer.
And that means that if you will change the dull layer, it will necessarily affect the C layer, making
the whole component much less modular.
Second loose coupling.
We will talk about this concept much more in the next lecture, but suffice to say that we need this
layer to communicate with each other in a way that will have the minimum impact when there is a change.
Let's see an example for this which will explain this concept.
Let's say this is a code in the layer that calls to the doll.
The specific code is written in Dotnet, but it holds true for any other language too.
As you can see, the code references directly the doll classes using the new keyword.
Although easy to implement, having a direct reference between layers will render them strongly coupled.
What this means is that if you will try to switch to other doll, we will have to touch all the code
that references it from XBL.
And that's bad.
The correct way of referencing layers is via dependency injection when the calling layer references
only an interface representing the desired functionality but not the concrete class itself.
Later, when we switch to other implementation, the code will not be affected since it wasn't referencing
the doll in the first place.
This concept is called dependency injection and we will discuss it later in this section.
The third concept is exception handling between layers.
Now, while the first two concepts are quite known, this one is more obscure and not all architects
are familiar with it.
The exception handling concept states that each layer must hide its inner exceptions and not let the
layers above it to know about it, but rather let them add generic non specific error message.
For example, let's say our doll works with MySQL database.
Now database exceptions tend to be very specific, which is good since it helps us pinpoint the problems
and fix them.
The problem is that this exception is thrown as a MySQL exception class and it contains data about the
inner workings of the database.
One of the most important concepts of the layer architecture is that each layer is encapsulated and
does not expose info about its inner workings.
If the doll will throw this exception, that means the bee will know the doll is using MySQL, while
it should be completely oblivious to its inner working.
So the correct pattern here is for the doll to analyze the exception, write it to a log and create
another exception called, for example, data exception with a generic error message that there was
a problem accessing the data store.
This way the only thing the bell knows is that the doll has some problems with the data actions, which
is fine because that all it has to know about the doll.
So these were the three concepts that make a good layered component.
Now, there is an additional point I would like to cover.
You might have heard about a concept called an entered application or a three tiered application and
wondered what it is and what is the difference between tier and layer?
Well, it looks like those terms, tier and layer are often interchangeable, but they shouldn't, and
there is actually a big difference between them.
A layer is what we talked about, a piece of code that is part of a component.
A component, let us all remind ourselves, is a code collection that runs in a single process.
There is no networking involved when the various classes in the component communicate with each other
and they all share the same computing resource tier.
On the other hand, is a distributed piece of code.
It's deployed independently and communicates with other tools via network protocols such as Http.
So when talking about a three tier application, what we actually mean is that the application has three
independent components deployed across the network that communicate using the network, which is completely
different from layers which are part of the same process.
Okay, so that concludes our discussion around layers.
Keep in mind that layers are almost always a good idea and it should be your default pattern for implementing
components.