It's now time to meet one of the most important acronyms in the software development and architecture
world, the Solid.
This acronym, coined by Bob Martin in the year 2000, represents five code design principles that,
when implemented, make the code easy to understand, flexible and maintainable.
Solid stands for Single Responsibility Principle Open Closed Principle.
Liskov Substitution Principle Interface Segregation Principle and Dependency.
Inversion Principle.
As we will see in a minute, all these principles are actually quite common sense, and you won't find
any huge surprises here.
However, we sometimes tend to forget the obvious, and it's good to have a solid reminder.
See what I did here to make sure we will still implementing them.
So let's dive into these five principles.
The single responsibility principle states something quite simple.
Each class, module, or even method should have one and only one responsibility.
Or in other words, a single well defined functionality.
And this functionality should be fully encapsulated within this class or module.
Let's look at an example.
Let's say we have a system that logs all its activity.
Now, when writing to the log, there are two main questions that should be answered.
First, what should be written, including the content of the log message and its format, which is
usually Json or XML.
And second, where should it be written?
Log records are usually sent to a file, a database, an event log.
ET cetera.
And this should be determined and handled as part of the logging process.
The Single Responsibility Principle states that these two questions should be answered by two separate
classes.
One is responsible for composing the message and the other will handle the actual writing.
So instead of a single method that performs the two tasks, we will have two classes.
Each performs those tasks separately.
The reason behind the single responsibility principle is that when a change is required, it will affect
only a well defined code module and we won't need to look for other obscure places in the code that
might be affected by the change.
This encapsulation will make our code very easy to maintain and quite flexible.
Next, the open close principle.
The open closed principle states that a software entity should be open for extension but closed for
modification.
What this means is that in order to change behaviour of a software entity, for example class, we won't
need to modify its code and then recompile and redeploy it.
But we will have means to extend its functionality without touching the code.
This principle is closely related to the extensibility quality attribute we talked about in the previous
section.
There are multiple ways to implement this principle.
The most common of them is the inheritance capability in object oriented languages, either inheriting
a concrete class or an abstract class.
We achieve the same goal extending functionality without modifying the code.
Of course, other types of extensions, such as plug ins, are also widely used and fulfill the open
close principle.
The reason behind this principle is quite clear We want our code to be as flexible as possible and enable
us to make changes quickly without modifying and compiling existing code.
The next principle is the liskov substitution principle.
This principle might sound a bit more complex than the other principles, but don't worry, we will
explain it.
The principle states that if s is a subtype of T, then objects of type T may be replaced with objects
of type S without altering any of the desired properties of the program.
On first look, this might look similar to polymorphism definition in object oriented languages.
Remember that polymorphism basically states that type can be replaced by its subtype without breaking
the code.
But there is a fundamental difference between the two.
The Liskov substitution principle does not talk about coding or compiling, but on something called
behavioral subtyping.
Let's explain it through an example.
Say we have a code that needs to send mail.
The code calls a class named mail sender and calls its send method, which, as you probably guessed,
sends the mail.
A few months later, the developers come up with a better mail, sending class called Advanced Sender,
which inherits from the original mail sender.
The developers want to substitute mail sender with advanced sender in their code.
The Liskov substitution principle says that when doing this substitution, the behavior of the send
method should not be changed.
If the original method only sent the mail, the new one should do the same.
There should be no new functionality that is unexpected by the calling code, such as throwing new exceptions
as a result of the substitution.
For example, if the new method not only sends the mail but also automatically sends a copy of the mail
to a central archive inbox that will break the principle and should be avoided since it breaks the behavior
of the original type.
The reason behind this principle is to avoid hidden behaviors that were not intended by the calling
code, thus making the code much more difficult to debug and to maintain.
The next principle is the interface segregation principle.
This principle states that many client specific interfaces are better than one general purpose interface.
Again, let's look at an example.
Let's say we have a class that handles data processing.
The class begins small with two methods read data and validate data.
An interface named data processor was created that defines those two methods.
While working with the class, additional methods were added to it that handle more tasks such as decoded
data, encoded data and send data to external system.
This method were added to the interface too.
Now what?
We've got a bloated interface with five methods that must be implemented by a single class.
Remember the single responsibility principle.
If you take a look at the class, you can see clearly that the class breaks this principle.
It now handles three tasks handling data, decoding encoding it and sending it.
The developers saw it too, and decided to split the class to three separate classes.
However, they now have a problem.
The interface forces them to implement all those methods using a single class.
The interface segregation principle says we better create multiple thin and well-defined interfaces
than a single general purpose one.
So in our case, instead of a single interface with five methods, we would be better off with three
interfaces with 1 or 2 methods.
This way our code can be modular and flexible and keep the single responsibility principle.
The last principle is one we have already talked about in the previous lecture.
The dependency inversion principle, also called dependency injection.
If you don't remember.
Head back to the previous lecture and watch it again.
And that's all about solid acronym.
Again, the principles here are all common sense, but it's a good reminder and will help you keep the
code clear, flexible and easy to maintain.