Imagine this.
It's 2 a.m. You are sleeping in your nice, comfortable bed, dreaming on unicorns and rainbows.
Suddenly the phone is ringing.
Confused.
You're sitting up blurry eyes and all and answer the phone.
Your hysterical boss is on the other side screaming about a problem with the mission critical software
you have just designed and commanding you to come straight away to the office and help the developers
who have no clue what's going on.
From this point, there are two alternate storylines.
In the first you hurriedly dress, forget to brush your teeth, eats something in a hurry, drives like
crazy, meets the developers and spending three very stressed halls looking at the code until you finally
find the culprit, which happens to be a null parameter no one expected.
In the second storyline you tell your boss, Oh, look at the logs.
They are on that network drive and go back to sleep.
Logging is important, even very important.
In fact, it's so important that this is the first component I always design when working on a new system.
No matter how simple the code is or how urgent is the system, never ignore the logging.
A good system uses logging for two purposes one to track errors.
If there are any exceptions during the system's activity, the system will write those exceptions to
the log, complete with all the relevant details, full error message stack trace, inner exceptions,
user details, and so on.
This way when an exception will happen and let's face it, they always do.
Eventually you will have a great starting point to investigate the exception.
You will know where to look for the details and understand immediately what are the causes of the exception.
The second purpose is to gather data.
Logs should not be used only for exceptions, but to collect and store operational data on the system.
For example, using logging, you can find out which model is the most visited by users and which one
is less popular.
You can store performance data and find out which methods perform poorly and which ones are blazingly
fast.
In fact, if the logging is really massive, you can reconstruct a specific user flow throughout the
system and understand his behavior.
This is priceless data for any system.
Note that it doesn't really matter where will you store the logs?
It can be in files, in database in event log.
Any place is good as long as you actually store the data and can access it.
There are a lot of log analysis tools in the market today.
Kibana one of the most popular and I urge you to use whatever tool you want as long as you keep logging
the hell out of your application.