Let's talk about deadlines.
Douglas Adams, the author of The Hitchhiker's Guide to the Galaxy Series and more great books, had
a great quote about deadlines.
I love deadlines.
I love the whooshing noise they make as they go by.
Well, don't we all?
But seriously, deadlines are a major factor when designing our architecture.
When deciding on the architectural patterns we are going to use, we must be aware, even vaguely.
How long will it take to implement them?
And how does it relate to the project's deadlines?
For example, remember our messaging method discussion?
If you remember, we said that building queuing mechanism will take longer than using rest API.
This is something that should be factored in when deciding on messaging platform on large projects.
This is usually not a problem, but when working on smaller systems with tight deadlines, always make
sure the architecture can be actually implemented in the given time frame.
If you are not sure about that, the best thing to do is to consult with the development team leaders.
They will usually be familiar with the developer's capabilities and will be able to estimate the work
required for the architectural implementation.
Using this valuable information, you will be able to make an educated decision that factors in the
project's deadline.