When selecting the technology stack, which is one of the most important parts of designing a system,
always factor in the existing dev team knowledge and skills.
Deciding on a technology stack that the dev team is not familiar with might cause two problems.
The first is delay to the project development.
The developers will have to dedicate time for training to make them familiar with the new technology.
This will have effect on the project schedule and can lead to late delivery.
The second potential problem is low quality.
Since the system will be the first for the dev team to be developed in the selected technology stack,
the developers will not have experience with the platform and will not know how to avoid common pitfalls,
implement best practices and take advantage of some hidden gems found in every development platform.
Now, it should be noted that not all platform migrations are created equal.
For example, for backend developer to migrate from Dotnet to Java might require some effort, but at
the end of the day, these are quite similar platforms.
And if the developer did a good job with Dotnet, he will probably be a good Java developer.
On the other hand, a Windows desktop developer migrating to Python backend development will have a
really hard time becoming a good Python developer.
Not only desktop development is conceptually very different from web development and requires a different
mindset.
The platforms themselves are completely different.
They move from object oriented statically typed language such as dotnet to the dynamic.
Python might not be easy.
So to summarize, when evaluating various technology stacks, always check what the current development
team's skills are and try to understand the effect it will have on the project's schedule and quality.