One of the biggest temptations when designing the architecture is to recommend various tools for the
various architectural aspects.
Tools like engines, business flow managers, NoSQL databases and more are quite common recommendations
for modern day architecture.
Problem is, those tools need someone who is familiar with them and can maintain them.
Now, if the organization's IT department possesses the skillset to maintain a shiny new NoSQL database.
All is good, but what happens when it's not?
What often happens is that the development team becomes the support team for these products and the
developers become experts in installing and maintaining them.
And that's not a good thing.
Developers should develop.
That's the best use of their time.
This is what they are paid for, to develop, not to be dba's, not to configure MQ series, not to
dig through support articles of MongoDB and the architecture you design must factor this in.
You must make sure that when recommending a new product to be included in the system, there will be
someone other than the development team to take care of it.
If that's not the case, then make a very careful analysis of the effort needed to maintain the product
and check with the developers whether they can handle it.
Note that if the product is a new, shining one, the developers will often be very excited about it
and will ensure you they can handle it.
Don't take it for granted.
Excitement fades over time and when this will happen, the developers will be left with a boring and
mundane task of maintaining a product instead of writing code.
So the bottom line is this Whenever possible, do not include products in the architecture that have
no one assigned for taking care of them.
Always prefer products that department knows and support.