Welcome to the architectural document section.
In this section, we will explore the most important product of the architect's work, the architectural
document.
In this document, the architect describes the architecture that was designed as well as the various
requirements functional and non-functional.
The technology stack and more.
In fact, the architectural document includes almost all the concepts and information discussed in this
course up until now.
The architecture document is a cornerstone of the application development, and no development should
begin before an architectural document is created and the developers fully grasped its contents.
In this section, we will deep dive into this document, understand what its goals are, who is the
audience and what is its structure.
Remember that this course has a very special bonus, a complete full blown, ready to use architectural
document which you can download and use as a template for your architecture.
You can find this document in the resources of the next section where we will discuss a case study for
the architecture process.
So remember, even if you feel you don't fully understand the role of each section in the document,
you will be able to see it in its full context in the actual document.
Let's go.