So what is the goal of the architectural document?
Why do we have to invest so much time carefully crafting such a comprehensive document?
Well, that's a very good question, and let's try to answer it.
First and foremost, the architectural document is a foundation of the development efforts of the system.
It describes what should be developed and how.
As a rule of thumb, no lines of code should be created before the development team read through the
architecture document and made sure they fully understand what should be done and how.
The document outlines the technology stack and the various components and services that comprise the
system and how do they communicate with each other.
Without this knowledge, the development team will have no idea what should be developed.
When following the document, the team will be able to develop a well thought of fully documented,
fast, secure, reliable and easy to maintain system.
This cannot be accomplished when such a document is not present.
So this is the first and the main goal of the document.
But actually there is more as we will see in this section.
The document also describes the functional and non-functional requirements.
In many cases, this is the first time such requirements are expressed on writing, and this is the
first time the customer is able to see it in formal form.
For the team, this is a great opportunity to validate the requirements and make sure together with
the customer that he gets what he actually wants.
So these are the goals of the document.
Let's move on and talk about some more aspects of it.