One of the hottest debates in the architect community is the format of the architecture document.
There are some standards that are sometimes used when writing the architecture document that define
various kinds of charts and diagrams to make the architecture easier to understand and implement.
One of the most famous standards is UML.
UML is defined as a modeling language that helps visualize the design of a system.
It consists of software concepts such as activities, components and interactions, as well as diagrams
visualizing the system design such as class diagram and use case diagram.
However, I am usually not using UML in my architectural documents.
The reason for that is quite simple.
Remember the documents Audience.
Good.
Most of the audience will not be familiar with UML and will have no idea what the meaning of the various
diagrams and terms.
And if the document contains a lot of this stuff, you will find yourself wasting a lot of time explaining
in plain English or whatever your local language is.
What did you mean and what should actually be developed?
In my experience, after designing hundreds of system, the most effective architecture document is
the most simple one, meaning just use plain English.
Describe in simple words what the design of the system is.
Don't use too many buzzwords all over the document.
Try to get into the mind of your readers.
Will they understand what you are trying to say?
Now, sometimes you will want to visualize various concepts of the design.
You will see that in the document we will discuss later in this course.
For this, use the software you have in hand.
It can be PowerPoint, Visio, Apple keynote, whatever suits you.
Just make sure the visualization is clear and concise and of a high quality and not cluttered with unnecessary
items and shapes.
Now, if your client specifically wants UML diagram is a document, and I had only one such a client
in my whole career simply go through some UML tutorials and create the diagrams using tools such as
Visio.
If you are fluent with PowerPoint, you can quite easily use it also for these diagrams.
So to summarize, the architecture document should be simple Use plain English to describe the requirements,
concepts and design and use your favorite charting tools for visualizations.