So what is the structure of the architectural document?
What are the sections and topics it must have in order to be as effective as possible?
Let's review the various parts of the document before deep diving into each one of them in the next
lectures.
First background.
This is where you, the architect, writes down the role and motivation for the new system from the
business point of view.
Notice there are no technical or architectural content in this section.
Next, the requirements.
This is a very important part of the document as the requirements dictate much of the architecture.
After the requirements comes the executive summary.
This is the part that CXOs will read as well as the project manager, QA leader and other non development
related functions.
This is usually the last section to be read by them and it should give a high level overview of the
solution.
Next is the architecture overview.
In this section, we will lay out the high level architecture painting the big picture of the solution
and following the architecture overview are the components.
Drill down.
This is where most of the work is done, and that's the core of the document.
It contains a practical, detailed architecture of the various components in the architecture, including
technology, stack, architectural details and implementation instructions.
So let's examine each section in detail.