The first section is a background section.
This is a short section one pager.
Max and its target audience is all the team and management members.
In this section you should describe briefly the system you are working on from a business point of view.
The section should describe, at minimum, the main role of the system.
For example, managing the HR of the company.
If it replaces an old system, describe why the old one should be replaced.
For example.
It requires too much maintenance and is based on outdated technologies.
And what is the expected business impact?
For example, streamlining HR tasks and increasing HR employees productivity by as much as 20%.
Now, the section might seem a bit out of place.
After all, we can safely assume that team members are already familiar with the system they are working
on, and this section will have nothing new to say about it.
So why is it here?
Nevertheless, the section is incredibly important and for a few reasons.
First, it displays your point of view of the system.
If someone has some comments to make on it or if an error was found, it's better to have an opportunity
to correct it as soon as possible.
And the first section is a great place for that.
After all, all the other sections build on this one and if it's not accurate, they should probably
be fixed too.
Second, it shows the management that you did your homework and that you are geared towards business
results and not just a tech geek.
This distinction is super important and gives confidence to the CEO and project manager that you are
someone they can talk to and will not drown them.
In a confusing techie lingo.
This is the reason this section should not have any technical details or architectural terms.
No microservices, no programming languages, no clouds, nothing.
Just a simple text describing what the system should do from the end user point of view.