The next section in the architectural document is the requirements section.
This is also a short section, usually no more than one page, usually less.
And its target audience is all the team and management members.
In this section we are going to describe the various requirements from the system.
Now, as you probably remember from previous sections, there are two types of requirements.
Functional requirements that describe what the system should do and non-functional requirements that
describe what should the system deal with.
Just a quick reminder.
Non-functional requirements specifies the required performance, expected load and data volume, SLA
and more.
Note that as opposed to functional requirements, these requirements do not describe what the system
should do, but rather what is the environment the system is expected to work in and with what it is
expected to deal.
The requirements section in the architectural document describes briefly both types of requirements.
Note that this section should be brief and the requirements should be listed in a bulleted list.
No more than three lines per requirement.
Now you might be asking yourself and me, why do we need this section?
After all, similar to the background section, the team is well aware of the requirement and should
be reminded of them.
Well, that's a very good question and let's try to answer it.
There are two important reasons for including the requirements in the architecture document.
First, similar to the background section, this section is included in the document to allow the readers
to comment on the requirements and to make sure everyone is well aware of what the system should do
and under what conditions it's supposed to work.
This is a great opportunity for you to validate your understanding of the system and make sure that
whatever you design solves an actual problem for the customer.
Second, remember that the architecture is designed against a well defined requirement.
A lot of the architectural characteristics such as redundancy, messaging, data storage and more,
are designed in light of a specific requirement.
For example, if there is a non-functional requirement that a message should never be lost no matter
what, then perhaps you will go for a queue based messaging mechanism.
If the requirements change and suddenly there is some tolerance towards message losses, the architecture
might change and we will recommend a rest API based messaging instead.
For this reason, it is extremely important to lay out the exact requirements, especially the non-functional
ones in the architecture document.
This way you make it clear what are the requirements that dictated the architecture and makes sure everyone
knows that.
Now note that this section is by no means a replacement for a design document created by a system analyst.
It gives a high level overview of the requirements and is mainly a talking point list, not a full blown
document.
Therefore, do not describe all the nuances and intricacies of each requirement.
A short, concise description will be enough.
So how is this section structured?
Well, first are the functional requirements and provide a list of the main functional requirements,
usually no more than five requirements.
Remember, use a bulleted list with no more than three lines for each requirement.
For example, here is a partial requirements list that can appear in a document.
Next comes the non-functional requirements.
In contrast to the functional requirements.
It's extremely important to be extremely accurate and specific in this list.
The reason is that while functional requirements are well documented in other design documents, non-functional
requirements are usually not included in any other document other than the architectural document.
For this reason, make sure the non-functional requirements list, while short and concise, contains
all the necessary details for the readers to fully grasp the requirements.
Here is a sample list of a non-functional requirements.
So we have talked about the requirements section.
Let's move on to the next one.