Our next section in the architectural document is architectural overview.
This section is usually a long one and can reach to up to ten pages.
Its audience is the development team and the QA lead.
The architectural overview section provides a high level view of the systems architecture.
Its goal is to present the architecture to the team and to explain its structure and logic.
This section does not deep dive into the specifics of any component of the architecture.
This is saved for the next section, but it lays the foundation of the architecture and provides the
context in which the various components will work.
This section has usually three parts.
The first part of this section gives a general description of the designed architecture.
This part lays the foundation of the architecture by describing its type and the reasoning behind it
and the major non-functional requirements, for example.
This part will explain that the system will be, for example, a web based system and will outline the
reasons for this choice.
It will describe the major architectural pattern used such as microservices, rest API, stateless and
so on.
In addition, it can be stated in this part that this application must have an average performance of
50 requests per second.
It should be clear that this part lays the foundation for the rest of the architecture that will be
built on top of it.
The second part is a high level diagram of the architecture.
This diagram describes the general concepts of the architecture using the various services, data stores
and interactions so that the reader will comprehend what the various components of the architecture
are and what is the responsibility of each one.
As mentioned before, there is not a single formal standard for visualizing architectural concepts,
and I'm using PowerPoint for that.
Let's look at a typical architecture diagram taken almost as is from one of the recent architectural
documents I've been working on.
As you can see, this diagram contains three types of elements services depicted as black rectangles,
interactions displayed as arrows and data stores represented as cylinders.
The diagram shows the various parts of the architecture.
It displays the services that together assemble the system, the role of each one, where they place
their data and the interactions between them.
Don't worry if you are not familiar with every term in this diagram.
For example, we did not discuss the Mqtt protocol.
This is a specialized protocol used extensively by Iot devices but is less common in more traditional
applications.
When the team will see this diagram, the developers will understand what are the components involved
in the system and why they are there.
This will be extremely helpful later when we will deep dive into each component and the developers will
already be familiar with the component and its role in the grand scheme.
It's important to note that the diagram is a logic one there is no mentioning of servers, networks,
switches, network drives, load balancer and such.
This is a strictly logic diagram displaying the logic components of the architecture do not mix physical
hardware with logic architecture.
The third and last part of the overview section is the walkthrough of the diagram.
In this part you will describe the various parts of the diagram and the role verbally.
This part walks through the diagram and explains each and every component in it.
It describes in simple words what is the exact role of the component, what is its functionality and
what interactions it has with each and every other component.
In addition, it describes the data that is stored in the components data store, if there is one.
This part is extremely important since a diagram cannot convey all the intricacies of the architecture.
It's important to include any logic details that you think will be relevant, such as the components,
users expected load, future extensions and more.
You will see a complete example of this part in the architecture document.
You will get on the next section of this course.
Now let's talk about technology stack.
What is the exact section in the document where the technology stack should be described?
Is it here in the overview section or in the next section that deep dives into the various components?
Well, the answer, as you might expect, is it depends.
If the system has a single technology stack and all its components will be built using this stack.
Then the overview section is a great place to write about it.
On the other hand, if the stack is different between the various components, it should be described
per component, since in modern systems there are usually more than one technology stack used.
I describe this part in detail in the next section, so let's drill down.