Welcome to the Soft Skills section.
In order to be a great architect, it's not enough to be well-versed in technology stacks, architectural
patterns, and coding best practices.
A great architect must have great soft skills.
These soft skills are essential when communicating with a project team from the developers to the project
manager and even the CTO and CEO.
Let's think about it for a moment.
A software architect is in a very unique position in the organizational tree.
She has a very deep knowledge about the application and its architecture, and she is expected to guide
the development team about the actual implementation.
But in reality, she has no authority over them.
She can't command the team What to do.
She can only recommend.
Now, if the architect is an arrogant, righteous person that makes everybody else feel inferior, no
one will want to work with him.
And as a result, no one would want to implement the architecture.
The architect must be able to make the team do what he wants without the actual authority over them.
This is called influence without authority, and this is one of the biggest challenges in the software
world.
You don't want to make the developers do as you say because they have to, but because they want to.
In this section, we will explore some soft skills that will greatly help you improve your communication
skills with the team and make them want to work with you.
Learning and internalizing these skills will make you a better architect, someone who is extremely
nice to work with and as an added bonus, also a better person, which is always good.
So let's go.