One of the most important soft skills that not enough architects possess is listening.
Sounds quite simple, I know, but I've met countless architects that behaved as if they already know
all that is to know about software, architecture, technology requirements and the specific project
and were simply not pleasant to work with.
One of the key factors in a successful teamwork is the ability to listen and to assume you are not the
smartest person in the room.
This assumption, regardless if true or not, will help you become a better team player and as a result,
a better architect.
Think about it.
If you are not the smartest man in the room, then you should probably listen to what the other people
in the room have to say.
They might have some clever thoughts worth sharing and using.
You know, collective wisdom is almost always better than a soloist work.
Even if you are sure you have just designed the best architecture possible.
Always assume you forgot something or wasn't aware of all the implications of the requirements or didn't
think about certain scheduling restrictions.
Talk about your work and more important, listen to what others have to say about it.
It will make your work so much better.