Let's face it, your walk is going to be criticized probably heavily.
You will be questioned on almost any design element in your architecture and will be asked to explain
the logic behind it.
Now, the worst thing to do with criticism is to get offended and attack back.
Doing so will put you in a compromised position and will paint you as a weak, unprofessional and immature.
This is not the place you want to be in.
Remember, there can be a lot of reasons behind criticism.
It can be a genuine questioning.
Someone actually wants to make sure the architecture is sound.
And she asks all the right questions.
Of course, in this situation you have to be very professional and provide all the facts and logic behind
your design.
Remember also, there is nothing wrong in saying, You know what, That's a good point.
I didn't think about.
Let me double check it.
And if it checks out, I'll fix the architecture document.
Such a response will only improve your image and reputation with a client and will make him appreciate
you even more.
Now, what do you do with a team member trying to mock you and make everyone think how bad the architecture
is?
By the way, there can be a lot of reasons for such a behavior.
I had a client a few years back that asked me to be the chief architect of a system and to have some
other guy as my, well, let's call it assistant.
This guy, which I'll call John, was a lot of trouble for me.
He didn't help at all, didn't perform any task I asked him to do and always questioned the design.
Only a few months later I found out John had hoped to be the chief architect of this project and was
extremely upset by not getting this job.
He expressed his frustration by constant nagging and questioning me.
So what do you do in this case?
First, do not get offended and never, ever attack back.
No matter how right you are, you have to stay professional and always be the bigger person.
Second, as before, always answer with logic and facts outraged people usually are at a loss of words
when faced with logic and facts, and that the best way to handle them if things get worse, set a meeting
with the manager and ask him gently to handle your own.
John.
But again, this is an edge case.
Not everyone who questions your design is doing so to mock, you always assume the criticism is for
a good cause and answer it calmly and professionally.