Public speaking is one of the most important skills of every professional.
Speaking at conferences, meetups, large meetings and such is a crucial skill for everyone who wants
to get promoted or seek new, better job.
But we are not talking here about every professional but rather about architects and architects specifically
must be able to speak in front of a large audience.
Remember, architects usually have no formal authority over developers, system analyzers or project
managers.
If an architect wants to influence, she should utilize her speaking skills.
In addition, architects are going to take part in many meetings.
Some of them are critical to the project's success, and their input is crucial.
So as an architect, you have to be able to stand in front of an audience and deliver a convincing,
effective speech.
Now, this is not a course about public speaking.
There are a lot of such courses out there, but I do want to highlight some of the more important aspects
of public speaking that will help you deliver an engaging and effective speech.
So let's go.
First, define a clear goal.
When you are going to talk in front of an audience, you must have a clear goal in place.
Why are you doing this?
Do you want to get approval for the architecture?
Do you want to improve your image?
Do you want to get a raise?
Whatever the reason is, you must define it and be laser focused on it while speaking.
This will help you improve your speech and make it more effective.
Second, know your audience.
You should always know who you are going to talk to and adapt your talk accordingly.
For example, if you are going to talk to business analysts, it probably a good idea to avoid a long
technical discussions.
They won't understand it and it will get them bored.
Third, be confident or if you are terrified, pretend to be confident.
People tend to respect and believe someone who is confident about what he has to say.
If your talk is full, with whom and a, it won't look good and people will lose you.
You have to let them know or think that you know what you are talking about.
Fourth, don't read ever.
One of the biggest mistakes public speakers do is to read from a slide.
Your audience is a smart, grown up people.
They know how to read.
Thank you very much.
The accompanying slides should be used to make a point and to visualize concepts.
Under no circumstances should they contain the content itself.
Fifth, maintain eye contact.
Always look at your audience and make sure to look at everyone.
One of the common mistakes of public speakers is to focus on a single attendee and look only at him
along the talk.
This will make the poor attendee feel uncomfortable and make the rest of your audience feel like you
don't talk to them.
Okay, so these were some highlights about public speaking.
And again, I would highly recommend looking at some resources and reading some books about it.
It's one of the most important skills and architects should have and you should be an expert in that
field.