And here we are at the last skill we will discuss.
And this is a simple yet very important one and it can be summarized like this Always keep learning.
We live in a dynamic world and the software world is even more so.
Things are changing in a blink of an eye.
Frameworks that were all the rage just three years ago are now completely forgotten.
You have probably heard of jQuery, Grant, AngularJS and Hadoop.
All these frameworks and engines were extremely popular not many years ago but now are almost never
used.
They were succeeded by better alternatives.
Now some don't like this fast pace, but that's a fact of life.
One of the most famous quotes in the business world is adapt or die.
Although its origin is not clear, it still holds a lot of truth.
You should always look around and check what's new.
If there are new patterns or technologies, follow them.
You don't need to immediately embrace them, but should definitely keep an eye on them.
So when time comes, you will know what to do.
Now how to do this learning?
Where can you find the knowledge relevant for architects?
Here is what I do.
My main sources for knowledge are blogs, articles and conferences.
There are a lot of blogs and articles sites dedicated to technology and architecture.
Some of the more popular are D Zone, InfoQ and O'Reilly.
Subscribe to these sites and you will get a lot of quality information.
In addition to that, I go once a year to a conference about software and architecture.
My favorites are O'Reilly Software Architecture Conference, Infocus, Qcon, NDC and Microsoft Build.
But of course, you might find other conferences you find useful.
These conferences are a great opportunity for firsthand meeting with the most talented people in the
industry and for learning about the newest trends and developments you should be aware of.
And it's always fun to visit new places and meet new people.
So the bottom line is this Whatever method you pick, always keep learning.
Don't get left behind with outdated knowledge and skills.
Make sure you can contribute to your clients in this fast changing world.