Welcome to the requirements section of this course.
In this section, we will discuss the basis of all the software systems in the world, the requirements.
Every software is based on some kind of requirements.
Some kind of user needs to accomplish something, and the software helps him to achieve this something.
The requirement can be I want to apply filters on my photos or I need to communicate with my friends
easily, or even I need to be able to tune my audio recording, whatever is that the user need.
These are the requirements.
Of course, requirements are never left in such a high level.
During the development cycle, they become more detailed, so the developers will have a clear idea
of what they need to develop.
In this section we will discuss two kinds of requirements and we will see how they fit in the architect's
work.
Let's go.