When talking about systems requirements, we usually think along the lines of what the system should
do.
We expect the requirements to deal with the following questions.
What are the business flows of the system?
For example, log in, storing photos, receiving and crunching, telemetry data and more.
What business services should the system have?
For example, logging service data access service Telemetry.
Receiver Telemetry control.
What does the user interface of the system looks like?
The look and feel, general guidance, responsiveness and more.
These requirements are called functional requirements.
You can identify those requirements from miles if they answer the question what the system should do.
They are functional requirements.
Functional requirements are, of course extremely important and no system should be designed and built
without them.
I had the pleasure of working on a system without concrete functional requirements, and I swore I would
never do that again.
However, for the architect, these requirements are important, but not as important as the other kind
of requirements.
These requirements are known as non-functional requirements and these requirements answer roughly this
question What should the system deal with?
Non-functional requirements Describe the various aspects of the system's operation and are not tied
to a specific behavior or logic.
The most common non-functional requirements are performance load data, volume, concurrent users and
SLA.
For those of you not familiar with all these terms, don't worry, we will cover them later in this
section.
Non-functional requirements are the requirements that really interest you as an architect.
I once had a client that asked me to design an architecture for a system he was planning.
On first sight, the system looked quite simple.
Simple rest services that receive data make some calculations, and store the results in a database.
Piece of cake.
Or so I thought.
Towards the end of our requirements meeting, I asked the client what would be the maximum size of the
data received by the service.
He looked at me with an I have no idea face made some phone calls, paid a little, came back to the
table and said, Well, 600MB.
Boom.
No architect in his right mind will expect a rest service to deal with such a huge request.
We had to return to the drawing board and ended up with a completely different architecture.
The rest services have gone and instead we had agents listening to a NoSQL database and waiting for
the data to be stored there.
And that's just one example of an architecture that gets turned upside down because of non-functional
requirements.
So now that we understand the difference between the two kinds of requirements, let's take a closer
look at them.