Well, we just say that non-functional requirements are the most important requirements and that the
architect should not under any circumstances, design the system without knowing what the non-functional
requirements are.
But it is equally important to be aware of the functional requirements.
Many architects feel they only need to skim over the functional requirements and concentrate on the
non-functional ones.
That's a mistake too.
Remember our definition of the architecture?
Remember that a good architecture must improve the business bottom line.
That won't be possible if you are not sure what the system should do.
So before diving deep into the non-functional requirements, this is a not so gentle reminder that the
functional requirements are equally important and you have to be well versed in them.