We have already explained what non-functional requirements are, but let's go over it again just in
case.
So while functional requirements define what the system should do.
Non-functional requirements describe what the system should deal with.
Systems can deal with many challenges during their operation.
They can experience large number of concurrent users.
They can experience servers crash, they can suffer extremely high load of requests and so on.
Non-functional requirements basically describe what is the expected environment for the system with
emphasis on edge cases.
If you will take a look at the Wikipedia page for non-functional requirements, you will see a long
list of those requirements.
In real life, however, there are five non-functional requirements that we will usually deal with.
Those five are performance load data, volume, concurrent users and SLA.
Let's discuss each of them.
Performance.
Well, that sounds like a simple requirement, right?
What is the required performance for this system?
Fast.
Easy peasy.
Well, not so fast.
See what I did here when talking about performance, there are two things we should keep in mind.
One, always talk in numbers, and two, latency and throughput.
Let's talk about the first one.
When the client asks for a fast system, your next question should be what is fast?
Fast can mean a lot of things in a lot of systems.
I've worked on systems where fast meant 30 milliseconds and on systems where fast meant five seconds.
The problem is that your client probably wasn't thinking on the exact number and you will have to help
him with that.
The rule of thumb is that when there is an end user at the end of the flow, we usually need the task
to be complete in less than a second.
When working in a B2B environment, that's a business to business, we are usually looking at faster
systems that can measure even 100 milliseconds per task.
The reason for that is that we human beings are less sensitive to subsecond delays and for us, a data
that is displayed in one second or 700 milliseconds looks almost the same.
While for a software running on a machine with CPU cycles of a few milliseconds, this will be a very
long time.
But again, the most important thing is to work out this number together with the client or system analyst.
The second concept is about latency and throughput.
Those two words define the way we look at performance and give us two points of view on it.
Let's begin with latency.
Latency answers the question How much time does it take to perform a single task in the application?
For example, how much time will it take for the API to save the user data in the database?
Or how much time will it take to read a single file from the file system?
You can see that the latency deals with the time it takes to perform a single task.
Throughput, on the other hand, answers a completely different question.
How many tasks can be performed in a given time unit?
For example, how many users can be saved in the database in a minute, or how many files can be read
in a second?
Now let's look at some numbers so we can understand better the difference between latency and throughput.
Let's say the latency of saving user data is one second.
This is quite slow, but let's stay with it for the sake of the discussion.
Now, what would be the throughput?
Can we know how many users can be saved in one minute?
The answer is a resounding no.
If the application is well designed, deployed on a strong hardware and knows its way around the threads,
it might have a throughput of 1000 users saved in one minute.
On the other hand, if the code is buggy and there are a lot of memory leaks and no concurrency at all,
we won't be able to reach a throughput of 60, which is the latency multiplied by 60, the number of
seconds in a minute.
So this is the difference between latency and throughput.
And when discussing performance, both of them must be mentioned and set.
Now let's talk about load.
The load non-functional requirement defines what is the load or quantity of the application will have
to withstand without crashing.
The exact definition of load depends on the exact type of the application.
For example, for a web API based application, the load will usually be defined as how many concurrent
requests are going to be received by the system without crashing.
Note that this requirement looks similar to throughput, which defines how many requests can be handled
in a specific time unit.
The difference between the two is that while throughput defines the time unit, the load defines the
availability of the system, meaning the system should be able to handle the load without crashing down.
For example, the performance requirement can dictate throughput of 100 requests per second, but the
system should be able to handle 500 concurrent requests without crashing, even if those requests will
take more than a second to complete.
This definition is important since the worst thing that can happen to a system is to crash under heavy
load.
Users can tolerate a slowdown when there is a load, but they won't like it if the system will crash
and burn.
So the best practice here is to always look at peak numbers.
For example, for an e-commerce website, the regular load might be up to 200 concurrent requests.
But on Black Friday, we are looking at more than 2000 concurrent requests.
In that case, we should plan for the extreme case because this is when it's more important for our
system to be alive and functioning.
Next is data volume.
This requirement defines how much data in gigabytes or terabytes our system will accumulate over time.
This requirement is important for a few reasons.
It will dictate what kind of database you are going to use, since not all databases can handle large
quantities of data equally.
It will also determine what type of queries we are going to write because a query in a table of a 100,000
rows will be completely different from a query in a table of 100 million rows.
And of course it will help us plan ahead.
The storage we need to allocate the data volume usually has two aspects.
One, how much data is required on day one and two, what is the forecasted data growth?
For example, a system might need 500MB on its first day and is expected to grow by two terabytes annually.
Of course, the growth period can be different and can be weekly, monthly, quarterly and so on.
Next is concurrent users.
This requirement defines how many users will be using the system simultaneously.
This requirement is quite similar to the load requirement, which also defines how many requests should
be handled by the system simultaneously, but with one week difference.
The concurrent users requirement describes how many users will be using the system, not how many users
will be performing requests.
This distinction is important when a user is using a system, there are a lot of dead times when no
action is actually taken.
For example, a user is asking the system to display all the data.
The system executes an API that goes to the database and retrieves the data.
This is an actual action.
Now the user is looking at the data.
During this time the system is doing nothing.
The API is not working.
The database just sits there and the network is silent.
So as you can guess, systems that can hold 500 concurrent requests will be able to withstand a much
higher number of concurrent users.
The rule of thumb says that concurrent users are ten times the number of concurrent requests.
So if the system should work with 500 concurrent requests, it can support 5000 concurrent users.
But this number actually depends on the type of system and the usage pattern.
SLA.
The last functional requirement we will discuss is the SLA.
SLA, which stands for Service Level Agreement, describes what is the required uptime for this system
in percentage.
This term is widely used by almost all public cloud providers.
One of the biggest competitions between them is on the SLA.
For example, Azure Cosmos.
DB takes pride with its 99.99% SLA.
This is translated to less than an hour of downtime in a year.
Take a look at the numbers.
The SLA has great influence on the design of the system.
For example, a system that cannot be brought down must have a sophisticated update mechanism that won't
require turning off the system while it's updating.
This is possible, of course, but it has to be designed this way.
One important thing to note about SLA is client expectations.
If you will ask the client what is required for the system, he will usually give you an answer along
the lines of 100% of the famous five nines, which is 99.999%.
When this happens, I usually tell him no problem.
For this we will need to build at least three data centers in different continents with independent
and dual power stations and automatic failover between them.
What do you say?
This generally brings him down to earth and we discuss more realistic goals.
So these were the most common non-functional requirements you will need to have for the system.
And again, never start working on the architecture before you have set those requirements.