So let's conclude what we have learned about nonfunctional requirements.
These requirements define what the system will have to deal with in terms of performance.
Load users.
ET cetera.
The client will usually won't be able to define those requirements by himself, and it will be your
job as an architect to help him define them.
And perhaps the most important lesson from this section never, ever design a system without knowing
its functional requirements.
The effect of those requirements on the architecture is huge, and you don't want to design a system
that will crash and burn on its first day in production.
In fact, the place of the non-functional requirements in the architecture is so important that they
have their own dedicated paragraph in the architecture document, as we will see later in this course.
So now that we know what non-functional requirements are and how to deal with them, let's continue
our journey in the architectural flow.