Let's talk about architects and academic degrees.
I'm often asked, what should I learn in university in order to be an architect?
Well, the answer is quite short.
I'm not aware of any academic institution that has a degree geared towards software architecture.
Of course, the usual computer science degree is always helpful, though not always mandatory, but
there is no specific degree that has to be taken in order to be an architect.
There are some courses and certifications that deal with architecture such as TOGAF, but they are geared
more towards enterprise architecture rather than software architecture.
So the bottom line is you don't have to have any specific formal education in order to be an architect.
It's mainly a matter of experience.