Welcome to the highlights section.
Right now you are probably scratching your head and trying to figure out if there is anything wrong
with your video player.
Don't worry, there isn't.
The highlights are a group of quality attributes that define the application's capabilities.
Almost all those quality attributes have a name that ends with ility.
Hence the Ilities in the title.
Quality attribute is an attribute of the system that describes a specific capability that is not related
to a specific functional requirement.
If that sounds similar to non-functional requirements, it's not a coincidence.
Quality attributes are closely tied to non-functional requirements and they describe what technical
capability should be used in order to fulfill the non-functional requirement.
For example, let's say we have the following non-functional requirement.
The system must work under a heavy load but should not waste money on unused resources.
This is one of the most common non-functional requirements, even if not defined with this exact wording.
In order to make it work, we will have to implement the scalability quality attribute.
Now, don't worry.
If you are not familiar with scalability, we will discuss it in a minute.
Suffice to say that the system must have the scalability quality attribute.
Once the quality attributes are set, the architecture must take them into account and make sure they
are implemented.
So the relationship between non-functional requirements, quality attributes and architecture is this.
Non-functional requirements define what the system should deal with.
Quality attributes Map those requirements to technical capabilities and the architecture describes how
those capabilities will be designed and implemented.
There are a lot of quality attributes.
In fact, if you will take a look at the Wikipedia page for quality attributes, you will find dozens
of them.
In this section, we will discuss the most important and common quality attributes and explain what
is their meaning and how they will affect the system.
Architecture.
The ilities we are going to discuss are scalability, manageability, modularity, extensibility and
testability.
So let's go and discuss scalability first.