As you can probably guess, manageability is the ability to manage the application.
Now, what does it mean?
Simply put, it's the ability to know what's going on with the application at any given time and to
take actions that will improve its work.
For example, a manageable application will constantly report its status to monitoring agents and let
them know when errors occur, when there is an exceptionally high load, when the ram is becoming dangerously
high and so on.
The monitoring agents report this back to a management console and then a decision can be made either
automatically or by a human operator to take some action, such as retrying the process that caused
the error or adding resources to cope with the load and with the situation.
The best way to differentiate a manageable system from one that is not is by finding out who is the
one that reports problems.
If it's the end user, then the system is not manageable.
And as a side effect, we have made your users a team which is bad on the other hand, if the system
itself report problems, the experience is much better.
The system will find out a problem is going to occur.
For example, a mass of request is received in a very short time and the response time degradates substantially.
As a result, the system alerts the monitoring agent about it and the operator decides to add more VMs
to support that load.
The end result is that the users don't even know there is a problem and the system is just humming along
happily.