The next quality attribute we will talk about is extensibility.
A system that implements extensibility or an extensible system is a system that its functionality can
be extended without modifying its existing code.
Let's explain it through a real world example.
Let's say we have an information system that has an API to query its data.
The API has a specific parameter called format that specifies the exact format of the data to be returned.
On day one, the system supports two formats Json and XML.
Everyone is happy with this format and the system works perfect.
Then one day a new requirement is received that requires a new format to be added to the list.
CSV.
Now on a naive system, the part that made the format was created as a single class that contains a
switch statement that checks what is the required format and executes code accordingly in the code built
like that.
The new requirement presents a serious problem.
We now have to modify a core piece of code and then perform all the tests it requires in order to ensure
we didn't screw anything.
In an extensible system, the process is quite different.
In such a system, we do not need to modify the original code but rather to extend it.
Now what does it mean to extend the code?
By extending we mean that we that we can add new code to the application and make it work without modifying
the original code.
There are various methods for such an extension.
For example inheritance, plugin framework and more.
One of the most common patterns is using a plugin framework with a dependency injection similar to the
code shown now.
In this code, the format name, which is XML, Json, or CSV or any other future format is passed to
the factory method.
Get formatter.
The factory method returns an implementation of the I formatter interface.
Note that the calling code has no idea what is the specific implementation that was returned.
We will discuss more about it later.
But the important thing to understand about the extensibility quality attribute is that such methods
exist and they allow us to extend the system's functionality without modifying its code.