In this section, we discussed the highlights, the family of quality attributes of a system.
We talked about the relationships between between non-functional requirements and these quality attributes
and explained that the quality attributes represent technical capabilities that stem from the non-functional
requirements.
We described five common qualities scalability, manageability, modularity, extensibility and testability.
I strongly recommend that each system you design will implement these ilities even if you are not sure
they are actually required in the system, they will probably be later in its lifespan.
I also recommend to take a look at the full list of the ilities in the Wikipedia page.
Some of them are really relevant for a very specific kind of systems, but others might come in handy
for your system as well.