Welcome to the Technology stack section.
In this section, we will discuss one of the most important and loaded tasks of the architect, and
that is selecting the technology stack of the system.
The selected technology stack will determine what languages, platforms and tools will be used during
system development and what are the skills required from the development team.
This decision is important for two reasons.
One, it's irreversible.
Once you've decided to use a specific platform and work has begun on this platform, you can't reverse
it.
It's not possible to decide three months into development that actually we prefer another platform.
Such a decision will result in a complete rewrite of the system and a substantial delay in schedule.
There are some architectural patterns that allow some kind of flexibility in the technology stack selection,
notably microservices.
But even there, it's not a good idea to switch platforms between each service.
Reason number two Decisions like that are often loaded with emotions and are made on a non rational
basis.
You will encounter situations where the development team would like to do a specific platform because
it's new, sexy and the team across the corridor already uses it.
It won't matter that this technology is inferior for the specific task in hand.
They will still want it.
So this decision has to be made with clear mind, must be heavily documented, and be a group effort.
And not only yours, the architect.
In this section we will discuss technology, stack alternatives for the front end, back end and data
store.
For each alternative, we will give a little background and discuss its pros and cons.
I hope this section will help you make an informed decision about the technology stack in your system.