So let's discuss our candidates for backend and service technology.
Now, to be clear, when talking about backend, we mean the server side of web apps and web API.
So our discussion here is about web apps, web API, console and services.
I'll call all of them backend for the sake of simplicity.
Now, just to set expectations, I'm not going to give you a definite recommendation about the platform
you should use for your backend.
That won't be smart since there are so many factors to be taken into account that without intimate knowledge
of the requirements, such a decision cannot be made.
What I am going to do is to lay out the main contenders and talk about pros and cons of each one of
them.
This will make your life much easier when selecting the platform.
Note Also, I'm not going to talk about every technology exists.
This will make the lecture too long and too boring.
I'm going to discuss the most popular platforms.
So here are our main candidates for backend applications in alphabetical order.
Dotnet.
Classic Dotnet, Core Java, NodeJS, PHP and Python.
So let's begin with Dotnet Classic or as we will call it here, simply Dotnet.
Dotnet was founded by Microsoft in 2001 as a response for Java.
It's a general purpose object oriented, statically typed platform with frameworks for desktop applications
called Winforms and later on WPF and for web apps and web API called ASP.Net Development in Dotnet is
done using Visual Studio.
In my humble opinion, one of the best development tools on the planet.
Dotnet is not cross platform, so it's relevant only for Windows based applications.
Its performance are okay, but there are faster platforms such as NodeJS.
Dotnet is a very mature platform with huge third party components and large community.
However, its roadmap is not clear since it looks like Microsoft is pushing Dotnet developers towards
Dotnet core.
Today, Dotnet is the default choice for Windows based application, mainly because of its great IDE
clear syntax and large community.
Next is Dotnet core.
You can call it Next Generation Dotnet and it aims to fill the gaps in Dotnet mainly cross platform
support and performance.
In my own experience, Dotnet core is a flexible and fast platform, but as of this recording, not
fully baked yet.
There are some glaring omissions, such as webhook support, partial odata support, PowerShell support
and more.
Dotnet Core apps can be developed using Visual Studio but also with VS code and other popular ides.
Dotnet core community is not that large, but is very vocal and is growing rapidly in the last Stack
Overflow Developers survey.
It's called Second among server side frameworks right after NodeJS in the long run.
Dotnet core would be a great choice.
Right now you should be aware about its gaps, but also about its amazing performance and capabilities.
The third one is Java.
Java has been around for a long time and it looks like it's here to stay.
Created in 1995 by Sun Microsystems, currently owned by Oracle, Java is one of the most popular platforms
in use today, like Dotnet.
It's a general purpose object oriented, statically typed language.
Its early forays into client side in the form of Java applets and later Java was not a huge success,
but the Android ecosystem with it.
Apps written natively in Java gave it a huge boost.
The server side Java is called Java.
EE recently changed to Jakarta Enterprise edition and provides everything you can expect from a server
side platform, including web apps, web API database access and lots more.
And all this in a cross platform environment.
Java has a huge community, sometimes suffering from too much self-criticism, but still provides great
support for everything.
Java.
In the last years it looks like the interest in Java on the back end has waned and new kids in the block
get all the attention.
But Java is still a great platform for web apps and web API.
Node.js is one of the youngest platform here, second only to Dotnet core.
It was founded on 2009 by Ryan Dahl and is optimized for highly concurrent web apps.
Its syntax is based on JavaScript, which makes it dynamically typed and it quickly gained adoption
because of its familiar syntax and great performance.
It's probably one of the fastest frameworks out there fighting with Dotnet core on the first place.
As mentioned, NodeJS is not targeted for long running processes, so don't try to build services with
it.
But for web apps that require a lot of short concurrent IO operations, it should be on the top of the
list.
PHP was founded in 1994 by Rasmus Lerdorf, which makes it even more mature than Java.
But in contrast to Java, which is object oriented statically typed language.
PHP very.
How can I call it messy?
It's very easy to learn, but that comes at a cost.
It sometimes looks like it was rushed out of.
The gate and was not polished enough.
However, it's one of the most popular languages out there and has a vibrant community.
PHP is laser focused on web apps and web APIs, so if you are planning a long running component, better
look somewhere else.
Last but not least is Python.
Founded on 1989 by Guido van Rossum and quickly became one of the most popular scripting language,
Python quickly gained momentum as the language that can perform almost any task.
You can find it inside applications written in other platforms, in machine learning systems and of
course as a web app or web API.
One of the strongest selling point of Python is its learning curve.
It is one of the easiest language to learn and is also very tolerant.
Python also has a large community which is known for its helpful members.
You can consider Python for almost any type of application, including web app, web API console or
service.
So this was a short review of the leading backend platforms.
Let's summarize it with the following table.
In this table you can see the main attributes of every platform.
I recommend you to use this table as a reference.
When time has come to select the technology platform for the backend service or console.