Before discussing front end technology, let's have a little reminder about what front is so front end
is a part of the software that is viewed by an actual user with his own eyes.
This is where we will display bottomless text, dropdown list, colors, messages and more.
So, naturally, when selecting a floating technology, we would like to select something with robust
visual capabilities, but something that will not make us work too hard.
But first, let's look back at application types we discussed and see which one of them actually has
a front end.
So Web apps definitely with defined Web apps as applications that run in the browser and display it
to the user.
We definitely have a front end here.
Web API, not so much client of Web API.
Other applications such as mobile apps, which by themselves might have front end, but the Web API
application itself does not mobile apps.
Yep, that's the whole point, is that it console will.
That is complicated.
Technically there is a user interface to a console application, but it's not built separately from
the console app itself.
And let's face it, there isn't going to be heavy investment in any console application user interface.
So for the sake of all of our discussion, there is no front end to console service.
Not the whole point of service is that it does not have user interface.
So no front end for Ubaidi desktop, of course, there is also desktop apps.
Varies greatly.
Is the common denominator of all of them is that the user can see them and interact with them.
So there is a front end to the desktop app.
OK, so let's go over the values front and types and see how to select the technology first.
Web apps, web apps by definition have Web based front end, which means we are going to use a combination
of JavaScript and services is the real question here is which JavaScript framework are we going to use?
The most popular frameworks at the time of this recording are angular and react.
There are other great candidates such as refugees, but I really want to focus on the most popular ones
with the largest communities.
So first, let's compare Angiulo and popularity.
As you can see on Google Trends, they are quite similar in popularity.
Looking at stack overflow dot com, we can see there are more questions regarding ungulates and those
regarding the act.
But since Angulo is older, it was founded on 2010 as opposed to 2013, the numbers are actually quite
close.
Let's compare the capabilities.
Angular is a full blown framework with a full set of capabilities A14 framework will need, such as
data binding state management, routing services and lots more learning.
And will.
I can take time and it won't come easy even to developers with a lot of experience in Web development.
React, on the other hand, is more libraries than a full feature framework.
It focuses on the user interface side and is great at it.
If other capabilities are needed than separate libraries should be used.
On the other side, react learning curve is much shorter and Web developers can get up to speed with
it in a matter of days, while angular training can take a few weeks, if not more so.
If you are looking for a one stop solution for all your web front needs and you have the time for training,
opt for angular.
Otherwise go for react.
OK, let's talk about mobile apps.
When designing mobile app, the first thing we need to do is to decide the development approach we are
going to use.
There are three main approaches for mobile app development, native hybrid and cross platform.
Basically, those approaches represent a trade off between development time versus capabilities and
your selection should be based on these factors.
Let's discuss these approaches.
Native apps as an answer.
Just use the native development platform for each mobile platform.
For example, native iPhone development can be done using objectivity or the swift language with the
development tool and using the iOS SDK.
Android apps, on the other hand, are developed mainly with Java using Android studio and the Android
SDK.
As you can see, AOS is native.
Environment is completely different from the Android one and you will have to have developers that expertise
in each one of those environments.
On the other hand, native of a full access to all the field capabilities, including camera, accelerometer,
Bluetooth, filesystem, text and more, you are not limited in any aspect and you can take advantage
of any feature you would like.
In addition, native apps are very responsive and will offer the best user experience.
Hybrid apps of the complete opposite of native apps happy to provide native rubber, usually with tools
such as a phone app.
And in it you will find a regular webpage complete with JavaScript and see if you can think of it as
Iglauer.
Fight Browsr with limited phone capabilities, but it's still a webpage and requires Internet connectivity,
accessing phone capabilities such as accelerometer or COMILLA can be a challenge without having to endure
a lot of limitations.
In addition, happy to provide inferior user experience compared to native apps in the graphics, performance
is limited.
In recent years, a new standard emerged called Progressive Web Apps, or Pittaway.
This standard allows up to behave much more like native apps with offline capabilities, improve the
hardware access and more.
The standard look quite promising and you should definitely keep an eye on it.
But it's still not mature enough.
Apple added support for Pittaway in iPhone only in U.S. relation with industry, and even in this version,
it's still limited and not on par with Android support.
So it's definitely worth looking into.
But perhaps too early to actually use.
The biggest advantage of hybrid lies in the development team is from the native wrapper, which do require
a bit of learning.
Everything else is the regular web development.
If your team knows how to develop web apps, they will know how to develop hybrid apps.
It's that easy in the middle between the native and hybrid apps we find across cross platform apps.
The cost platform approach works like this.
The development is done in a specialized environment not linked directly to any of the mobile platforms,
the leading growth platform environments.
Today, al-Samarie and React Native in summary, and you will develop in C Sharp using visual studio
while in real native.
The development is done with JavaScript using one of the many ideas supporting REAC native.
After the development is done, you compare the application and the result is the native up for the
selected platform.
You will be able to compensate for iOS and for Android and get native apps for both of them without
writing a single line of Java or objectives.
So pros of using this approach are clear.
We write the code once and it was on both platforms as native apps.
What are the cons?
There are a few.
First, there is usually a government supporting latent capabilities of the native operating system
and the cross platform tools always play catch up with the various mobile platforms.
In addition, cross platform apps do not work well with heavy graphics.
So if that is your plan, you will have to go to native apps.
Last but not least for some scenarios, you will still have to resort to native programming, especially
when accessing specific sensors.
So in this case, this is not your cost platform.
So let us summarize in this table, you can see the differences between the three approaches.
Use this table as a reference when selecting technologies for mobile apps.
I hope it will help you the way it helped me.
And now for the third and left front end up, which is a desktop.
Now, let's face it, if you are developing a desktop application which will run on a PC, most chances
are you are targeting Windows.
So I limit the discussion to Windows based desktops on Windows.
We have three options for desktop development windfarms F and you will Frome's is all this technology
introduced in 2001 together with dot net introduction.
It's similar in concept to older platforms such as the basics and is quite limited in its graphical
capabilities.
For example, try to implement rounded corners to a button.
It's possible, but oh boy, it's so hard.
On the other hand, developing in Wohlforth is quite easy and the a learning curve is short.
We have introduced in 2006 improved the situation dramatically.
It offers full control on the visuals and give complete freedom to visual designers.
You literally can do whatever you want, but it's always about it's much more complicated than windfalls.
In order to use WP, if you will have to learn new language.
Zemel, which similar to the email, functions as a markup language to the user interface.
Zemel is a very rich markup language and it's very easy to get lost in it.
It's even safe to say that an inexperienced developer can cause more harm than inexperienced, willful
developer.
Our last contender is GWP or Universal Windows Platform.
You WPEC effort done by Microsoft to unify all its screens like PC, Xbox, Windows Phone Service and
more to support a single UI platform.
The result of this effort is youwe which is quite similar to what was important differences.
First, it runs in a sandbox, meaning it does not have full access to all the operating system capabilities
similar to hybrid apps in mobile.
Second, as mentioned above, it runs on all windows with screen.
So if you want to develop an app for Windows and Xbox, that's the way to go.
Third, it's much less mature.
And so that summarizes the desktop alternatives.
In this table.
You can see the summary of the three alternatives you talked about with the main differences between
them.
As usual, you invited.
We use this table as a reference for your future system.
We walk on and now let's elect data technology.