In this section, we discuss the technology stack selection process and divided it to back end, front
end and data store.
I didn't try to declare a winner on each category, but rather to demonstrate what are the principles
that affect the selection and what are the parameters we should evaluate when making this selection?
I would like to emphasize again how important is a rational, educated selection and what is the impact
of selecting the wrong technology for the wrong reasons?
There are a lot of emotions in this discussion.
You will tackle dev teams that won't be ready to hear about anything which is not dotnet even if it's
clearly not the right choice for the system.
You will participate in heated discussions between Angular supporters and React supporters and you will
definitely be part of a meeting discussing NoSQL versus SQL from all the wrong reasons.
My best advice is stay out of the line of fire.
Bring to the table the rational voice backed by concrete numbers and factors.
Never get involved emotionally in such discussion.
It will harm your architecture and more important, your reputation.
Believe me, after the system will be implemented successfully using the technologies you recommended,
no matter how angry they were at the beginning, they will be thanking you at the end.