Welcome to the Application Types section.
In this section we will discuss the various application types and architect will work with one of the
first things an architect should do when working on a system is to determine what kind of applications
the system is going to be.
This decision is usually made after working on the requirements, either functional or non-functional.
In this phase, you have already learned what can be learned about the functionality of the system and
the environment it will be operating in.
And you can make an educational decision about the type of applications that best fits these requirements.
This is an important decision since each type has its own pros and cons.
Moreover, once the decision is made, it's usually not easy to switch to other types.
The most common application types are web apps, web API, mobile console service and desktop.
Let's go and discuss each one of them.