Well, I guess you can guess what this type is all about.
Mobile apps.
As their name suggests, are apps that run on mobile phones, specifically smartphones, probably Android
powered or iPhones.
Modern mobile apps connect with web APIs all the time for multiple purposes Logging, loading next levels,
storing user generated content, and much more.
Actually, there are not a lot of mobile apps, perhaps only games that can function properly without
internet connectivity.
Mobile apps will be used mainly for apps that require user interaction, for example, games or social
apps.
Front end for web API application for displaying various types of content.
For example, news and apps that are location sensitive and will benefit from the phone's GPS.