Console applications or command line applications, often called CLI, are applications that run inside
the command line of the operating system.
These applications have few common characteristics.
They don't have any fancy UI.
The only thing the end user sees are the lines of text displayed in the command line window.
They require some level of technical knowledge.
Console applications are triggered by typing a command in clear text, often with some parameters.
Normal end users who are accustomed to point and click applications will have a hard time working with
these applications.
They usually have a very limited interaction with the user, if at all.
In most cases, the console application might present some questions to the user in order to configure
its behavior, and then we'll start running.
This configuration can be set also via command line parameters.
They can trigger long running process as well as execute very short focused actions.
Console applications are used mainly for executing long running processes that do not interact with
the end user and short focused actions, such as exporting data that should be used by specially trained
power users.
It's important to note that the fact the application is a console application does not change anything
to its architecture or the architecture patterns and practices apply also to console applications.