Services are quite similar to console applications with two important distinctions.
They have no user interface at all as opposed to the command line window in the console application.
And they are managed by a service manager, which is a feature of the operating system that manages
the services.
In Windows there is one service manager, while on Linux there are a handful you can choose from.
The service manager starts and stops the services and also monitors their activity.
Since services cannot ask the user about their behaviors, they will usually have a configuration file
containing the required parameters.
Services are used for long running processes such as monitoring folder on the disk when no user intervention
is required.