Desktop applications are the poor boys of the app world.
In a world where web APIs and clouds are all the rage.
Almost nobody talks about desktop apps and for good reason.
Desktop apps are applications that run mainly on the PC.
It's important to differentiate it from rich client apps that access Web API and are only a thin visual
layer above the data.
I'm talking here about an application that has all its resources, including logic and data on the local
PC.
This application might be using the internet for some arbitrary tasks, such as validating license or
sending activity logs, but it will still be fully functional when offline.
Another aspect of desktop application is its UI or user interface.
Desktop apps are targeted for end users and they will usually have a great user interface.
One good example of such an application is Microsoft Word, which works with or without an active Internet
connection.
Of course, you will lose some capabilities when offline, such as cloud connectivity, but it is still
fully functional this way due to massive use of cloud computing and the ubiquity of internet connectivity.
Desktop apps popularity is dwindling.
You will use desktop apps mainly for user centric actions such as word processing or calculations and
heavy gaming.
But again, you can spend a lifetime as an architect without designing desktop apps even once.