We've gone through the most common application types you will encounter as an architect.
However, today in the cloud era, there are many more types of applications.
For example, one of the hottest trend today is function as a service implemented by the likes of AWS,
Lambda or Azure Functions, which allows the developer to write a short focused code segments and not
worry about servers, scale or SLA.
Applications built on these functions are not web apps or web API and represent a new type of applications.
But still most apps today fall into the categories we discussed.
One of the first tasks you will have when beginning work on a system is to determine which application
type is best suited for it.
Often a system will comprise of more than one application, and you will find yourself mixing and matching
various types in a single system.
For example, many web apps have in addition to the main application, also a service that run continuously
and performs maintenance tasks such as removing old data records, monitoring various processes and
so on.
This is quite common and you will probably encounter this type of systems in your job.