Welcome to the third section of this course, the architect's Mindset.
In this section, we will discuss one of the most important aspects of being an architect, which is
the architect's mindset.
If your current job is a technical one, such as a developer or a team leader, then you are probably
thinking about the work you do from a coding and development point of view.
But as you will see in this section, this is not always the most appropriate point of view for an architect.
The architect should often make a decision based on other factors which are sometimes foreign for a
developer.
But in order to be a really good architect, you have to adapt yourself to the new point of view, which
will make you a real asset for the organization.
So let's talk about this new mindset.