The biggest mindset change you have to make in order to be a good architect is to understand the business
your client or employer is involved in.
Now, this might sound trivial.
Supposedly everyone in the organization knows what the company is doing, right?
Well, that's usually only partly true.
I'm sure every Microsoft employee knows that Microsoft develops software such as Windows and Office
and that it has one of the largest public clouds in the world.
I'm also sure that every Amazon employee knows that Amazon sells a huge selection of items from books
to fresh food.
But that is not enough.
And let me tell you a story.
A couple of years ago, I was approached by a company in the Iot field.
It was a medium sized company with about 600 employees worldwide.
I was familiar with this company and I knew vaguely what they were doing, but I knew it wasn't enough.
So I grabbed my PC and began reading.
The day after we had the meeting, to their surprise, I was able to tell them about their founders,
their line of products, their revenue and profit.
And bear in mind, the company was not publicly traded at that time.
Competitors and so on.
This blew them out of the water and we agreed to work together on this very day.
But I'm not telling you this story to teach you marketing tactics, although it's a very effective one.
The real important lesson here is that in order to be of a real value to the organization, you have
to have a deep understanding of the organization's business.
You have to know what keeps the CEO awake at night.
You have to understand what its weaknesses and strengths are.
Who are they competing with and what is their growth strategy?
Only after you understand all this, you can start talking architecture and technology.
One of the most common mistakes made by architects is that they are looking at the systems they are
working on as a stand alone system, isolated from the rest of their organization.
But it can't work that way.
Every organization is a living organism with a lot of moving parts, and the architect must understand
how the system integrates into this living organism.
And what role does this part play?
So to recap, remember, always understand the business before you begin working on the architecture.