One of the most important aspects of the architect's work is to identify who the client is.
Now, that might sound a little stupid.
Of course I know who my client is.
It's the one who pays me.
Well, yes, but also no.
Let me explain.
In almost every organization, the architect is part of the IT department.
It doesn't matter whether the architect is an employee of the organization or a consultant who works
with the organization.
He is hired by the IT people.
But the IT guys have clients, and these are the end users of the application.
And these are the guys you should work for.
What does it mean?
It means that your mindset should be geared towards your client's client.
It means that with every decision you make, you must ask yourself what will be the effect of this decision
on your client's client?
It means that the comfort of your client's client is prioritized over the comfort of your client.
Let's see an example.
One of the recent systems I worked on was a system that displayed data based on the telemetry received
from remote stations.
One of the dilemmas we had is what to do when the database storing the telemetry is offline.
This was a scenario we had to consider since the IT department could not commit to a concrete SLA of
the database.
The solution we came up with was to display a clear message to the end user that there is a problem
with the system and ask him to try again later.
This is quite a common behavior for such a scenario.
However, the client asked whether we can find an intermediate solution that will allow him to view
the data but not make any modifications.
We thought about it long and hard and came up with a solution that made our architecture much more complicated.
We have introduced a dedicated caching layer that duplicated the data and was used when the database
was offline.
My client, which was a development team, worked much harder.
But my client's client, the end user, was extremely satisfied with this solution and praised our willingness
to help him and to think outside the box.
Now, you might say that working with a client is a system analyst job and not the architect.
This is usually correct, but sometimes a project is carried out without a system analyst on board,
and even if there is one, you still have to understand the client's environment in order to make the
best decisions for him.
In this case, the architect does not replace the system analyst, but it's a very good idea to join
her for some meetings and to meet the clients personally.
Sometimes you will see that your client, the IT department, does not view the client as a client.
They will refer to the end users as colleagues, co-workers, or even those annoying guys that always
have demands.
In this case, your work might be a bit harder.
You have to not only change your mindset, but also them.