Welcome to the case study section.
In this section, we are going to use all the knowledge gained throughout this course by designing architecture
of a real world application.
This will be a great opportunity for you to test your knowledge of all the topics we discussed and see
their usage in the real world.
The system we are going to design is quite similar to one of the systems I've been working on in recent
years.
This is not a toy system specifically designed to make your life easier, but a real world application
used by real customers serving real data and cost millions to design, develop and deploy.
I've changed some details in the system description to keep customers data safe, but other than that,
that's the real deal.
In this section I'll introduce you to the application and then we will go through all the stages in
the architecture process.
We will talk about requirements, map the components of the architecture, select the technology stack,
and then design the architecture of the various components and then get yourself prepared for a real
treat.
At the end of this section, you will have the opportunity to download a complete architecture document
containing the architecture of this application.
This is a real world architecture document, quite similar to the ones I prepare for my clients.
You are invited to read it and even better, use it as a template for the systems you are working on.
Be sure to listen closely to the usage guidelines of the document, and as long as you follow them,
it's yours to use.
This will make your life as an architect much easier and will boost your transition from developer to
an architect.
So let's go.