Our next service is a receiver.
Let's have a quick refresher.
The receiver is a service that receives the messages from the Iot devices and sends them to the queue
to be handled by the handler.
So first, what kind of application is this service?
Well, this is an easy one.
We said the devices send their messages via Http using the rest protocol.
So the evident conclusion is that the service is a web API which exposes rest endpoints.
Good.
That was really easy.
Let's continue to the next step which is selecting the technology stack.
Well, it turns out that this is also an easy decision.
We already decided that the first service is going to be based in Dotnet core and we will need a really
good reason to divert from this decision.
Using multiple technologies in a single application can create a lot of headaches if done for the wrong
reasons.
So let's see if there is any good reason not to continue with Dotnet core on this service.
So does Dotnet Core has a good support for web API applications?
The answer is a resounding yes.
It was built from the ground up to support web API applications using its ASP.
Net core libraries and has great support for it.
In addition, its web API performance are great.
Okay, so it looks like there is no reason not to use Dotnet core here and this is what we will do next.
Let's look at the service architecture.
Remember the layered architecture we discussed earlier?
Let's see if it's a good fit for this service.
When looking at this diagram that shows the classic three layers architecture, it looks like it's going
to fit exactly to our service.
But a closer look reveals a problem here.
Take a look at the bottom layer, the data access layer.
Remember what our service is supposed to do with the messages.
It's going to put them in a queue.
That's right.
There is no data store for this service.
Well, you can argue that queue is some kind of data store, but in reality we don't treat it that way.
But as a method for passing messages from one point to another.
So while our service definitely needs service interface, which is what the devices will talk to and
the business logic layer, which will validate the messages, we need to substitute the data access
layer with another layer.
In this case, we will create a new layer called queue handling layer, which will take care of the
various tasks of working with the queue, mainly adding the message to the queue.
And this is how the updated diagram looks like.
This is actually a great example of the strength of the layered architecture.
We had to replace an entire functionality of the system using queue instead of data store, and only
one layer was impacted by this.
The service interface and business layer have no idea something has changed.
The service interface still works with a business layer in the exact same way they worked before.
The change and the business layer will continue working with interfaces representing the data layer
and will have no idea the concrete implementation has changed.
So if you ask yourself why do I need a layer architecture?
I hope you've got your answer now.
Last but not least, we will be adding a logging layer to allow the service to log everything that's
happening during the receiving of the message.
Now look how the logging is represented in the diagram.
This is not a normal layer and it's not located between other layers.
It looks like a vertical layer or in more professional jargon, a cross cutting concern.
This kind of layer, which is not exactly a layer, is available to all the layers, which is logical
since all layers must be able to log.
What is going on with the messages are taking care of.
So all the layers will have a reference to a logging mechanism and will enjoy this cross-cutting concern.
Okay.
Now this is a good time to look back at the non-functional requirements defined for the system and make
sure our architecture is compatible with them.
There are actually two non-functional requirements that are relevant for this service.
The load non-functional requirement, which is set for 540 concurrent requests, while 500 of them are
from the devices and the message lost non-functional requirements that stands at 1% message loss allowed.
Let's begin with the load requirement at 500 concurrent requests.
We are quite comfortable with our design.
The architecture is fully stateless and easily scaled out.
Adding to that, the fact that the service does not do much other than adding the message to a queue
for the sake of performance and it looks like this service will have no problem complying with this
number.
And what about the message loss requirement?
Well, if you remember, we said earlier that the fact that the requirement is for 99% and not 100%
is a big difference.
And this is where we see that since 1% of the messages can be lost, a standard rest API is good enough.
The chance for more than 1% of requests to be lost in such an API is extremely low and since again the
service does not do much in the first place, we can be comfortable with this requirement.
If we had to make sure that no matter what, no message will be lost, we would have been in a much
more difficult.
Position and probably we'll have to implement complex failsafe mechanism to make.
Sure the message will always be received.
And that concludes our civil service architecture.
We now have a complete architecture for this important service, which includes its application type
technology stack and internal architecture, including logging mechanism.
That's great.
And we can now continue to our next service.