Our next service is the handler.
As you probably remember, the handler is responsible for validating the messages, passing them and
storing them in the system's data store.
One of the major factors that will influence the handlers design is the fact that the messages to be
handled are waiting in a queue after being placed there by the receiver.
This fact dictates the type of application of the handler service.
Remember how we selected the type of logging service?
Well, the handler service is quite similar in the logging service.
The log records were pulled from a queue by the service and then stored in a data store.
The handler service works the same.
It pulls the messages from a queue, handles them, and store them in a data store in the logging service.
This fact caused us to decide it's going to be a Windows service because there is no request response
execution model here, but a service that is always on and pulls the queue.
And the same goes for the handler service.
It is not a request response service.
It's always active and is busy pulling the queue.
So the handler service is going to be a Windows service too.
Good.
Next, the technology stack.
By now we already have two services for which we determined the technology stack.
The logging service and the receiver.
In both we went for Dotnet core.
Since it looks like there is no real reason to select other technology for the handler service since
there are no special requirements and it will be developed by the same teams who developed the other
services, we can be quite comfortable in using Dotnet core here too.
Okay, good.
And now to the architecture.
We are going to use the traditional layered architecture pattern here, same as in other services.
Let's examine what layers are relevant here.
First service interface.
Well, we don't have one.
This service does not expose any API.
It is always active and initiates the calls to the queue.
It's not waiting for request from other services.
So this layer instead of exposing API will orchestrate the work against the queue.
Specifically, this layer is responsible for timing the polling of the queue and executing the actual
polling.
Let's call this layer polling same as in the logging service.
Good.
Next layer is the business logic layer.
And yes, the handler service definitely needs such a layer.
This layer is responsible for validating and processing the messages which are typical jobs for business
logic layer.
Now note that in a real world app we would have discussed a plugin mechanism to allow dynamic loading
of validators and parcels for specific message types, and this is definitely the recommended approach
here.
But for the sake of simplicity, I'll leave that out for now and assume that the validation and parsing
are coded right into the business logic.
And last but not least, the data access layer.
This is an extremely important layer in this service and it's responsible for saving the handled messages
into the data store.
This is very relevant here and we will leave it as part of our layered architecture.
And of course, let's add the logging engine, which similar to the one we used in the receiver, is
vertical and accessible by all the layers.
Great.
So now we have the architecture for the handler service.
Let's move on to the next service.