Well, we now have a full system architecture in place.
That's great.
The next logical step is to put it in writing and create an architecture document.
So let's go through the various parts of the document and make sure we know what should go in each section
first.
Background.
Well, we already have the background here.
This section describes the IO2 system, its motivation and main functionality.
Then the requirements we have well defined requirements, functional and non-functional, and we just
need to write them down in this section.
Overall architecture is our next section and here we will outline the various services and the messaging
between them.
We have already covered this.
Then we are going to drill down to each service and describe what is the role of the service, what
is its technology stack and what is its inner architecture.
We have went through all this in the previous lectures and just the executive summary, as you probably
remember, the executive summary is the last section we will write, even though it appears at the beginning
of the document.
Of course, we already have all the knowledge required for the executive summary.
Okay, great.
It looks like we have everything needed for writing the document.