And as promised, here is your architecture document.
In the resources section of this lecture, you can find the full architecture document of the system.
We just discussed the IO2 system.
In the document you will find all the sections we talked about the background requirements, executive
summary, architecture, overview and components.
Drill down.
You will find there are all the decisions we made complete with the rationale behind them.
You will see there all the figures and diagrams that we used during our discussion.
You will find the functional and non-functional requirements.
You will see the technology stack dilemma that we had and what we decided to use.
You will find all the messaging methods we are going to implement and so on and so forth.
In short, you will find the full architecture we discussed formalized in an easy to read comprehensive
format.
Now the good part is this Feel free to use this document as a template for your future architecture
document.
One of the major tasks of every software architect is to craft the architecture document.
Using this document as a template will make your work so much easier.
Instead of beginning from scratch and trying to figure out what to write and in what order, the template
figures everything out for you.
The document sets the sections, their order and their desired content.
All you have to do is simply fill in the blanks and of course, feel free to use the i o to specific
sections as a foundation of your architecture.
However you choose to use this template, I'm sure it will help you become a better, more professional
architect.
One final note before you go and download the document.
Note that at the beginning of the document there is a copyright notice that states the template is based
on this course.
Please do notrillionemove this notice it's an important part of the document.
So now go on and grab the file after downloading it, take the time and read through it.
Make sure you are comfortable with its structure and contents and make sure you see the correlation
between it and the discussions we had in this section.
After you have read it, let's go to the next section.