Welcome to the Advanced Architecture Patterns section.
By now, we have learned about the most common architectural patterns such as stateless scaling, loose
coupling and layered architecture.
You will probably use these patterns in almost every system you will design, and I'm sure they will
serve you well.
However, these are not the only patterns exist.
The software architecture world is an ever changing and evolving world, and new patterns frequently
emerge.
In this section, I would like to give you a taste of some of the more advanced architectural patterns
exist today.
You will probably not use them in every system, but it's always a good idea to keep them in mind.
And when an opportunity presents itself, use them.
We are not going to deep dive into these patterns.
This will require a course of itself, but we will get the gist of these patterns so you will know they
exist when relevant.
So these are the patterns we will discuss.
Microservices event sourcing and seekers.
Don't worry if you are not familiar with these patterns.
That's why I'm here for.
So let's go.