Welcome to the Architectural Process section.
In this section, we will discuss the process of the architect's work in order to make the architecture
as useful as possible and to provide the maximum value to the client.
The architect should follow a well defined roadmap that at the end will lead to a practical and well
thought of architecture which will ensure the system is fast, secure, reliable and easy to maintain.
In this section we will talk about this process.
I will give a brief overview of each step in the process and describe its importance.
In later sections.
We will deep dive into each step and talk about what exactly should be done.
So here are the steps in the architectural process.
Understand the system's requirements.
Understand the non-functional requirements.
Map the components.
Select the technology stack.
Design the architecture.
Write the architecture document.
Support the development team.
Let's talk about these steps.