The first thing on architecture should do when beginning a work on a new system is to understand the
system's requirements.
Okay.
Well, actually, the first thing is to understand the system's goals, as we discussed earlier in this
course.
But an actual architectural process begins with the requirements.
Remember, the requirements describe what the system should do.
They usually begin with high level tasks such as allow end users to view telemetry data and often describe
also workflows, logical services and user interface elements.
Those requirements are usually defined by the system analyst who works directly with the client.
So in most cases, your first work meeting after the obligatory introductory meeting will be with the
system analyst.
In this meeting you will discuss the requirements of the new system and probably set dates for future
meetings on the same subject.