The next step in the architectural process is to understand the non-functional requirements of the system.
Non-functional requirements are a special kind of requirements that define some technical and service
level attributes of the system.
For example, the most common non-functional requirements are about concurrent number of users, heavy
loads, volumes of data and performance.
As we will see in a later section, the client and the system analyst are usually not aware of the non-functional
requirements and it's the architect's job to help them formulate those requirements.
For us, the architects, the non-functional requirements are much more important than the regular requirements.
I never begin to work on a system before knowing exactly what its non-functional requirements are because
so many architectural elements can be affected by those requirements.