The next phase of the architecture process is mapping the various components of the system.
The components are the moving parts of the system.
They represent the various tasks of the system functional as well as non-functional.
The component map serves two goals.
It helps you understand the system and its various parts.
It's a great way to communicate to the client your understanding of the system, thus making sure you
are not missing anything.
Note that the component map is completely non-technical.
You are yet to decide on the platform, the development tool, the database type.
This is just a map that displays the various capabilities of the system.