This is one of the most important steps in this process.
In this step, you are going to decide together with the development team, what will be the platform
on which the system will be based.
Usually there will be more than one technology to be used in most systems.
You will have to select the back end platform, the front end platform and the data store platform.
In addition, in some systems such as ones that are based on microservices architecture, you will often
select multiple back end platforms and perhaps also multiple data stores.
As we will see in the relevant section.
There are a lot of factors you have to consider when selecting the technology stack, and the selection
must be very rational.
A wrong technology stack can lead to failure of the whole system.