This is the heart of your work.
You already have the requirements, the non-functional requirements, the components and the technology
stack.
All that's left is to design the architecture that will glue all those together and will result in a
system that is fast, secure, reliable and easy to maintain.
We will learn about the qualities of a well-designed system such as loose coupling, stateless scaling,
caching, messaging and lots more and see how those qualities are used as the building blocks of the
architecture.
When you are done, you will have a complete architecture in place, but it won't be formalized yet.
Which brings us to the next step.