This is what you were waiting for.
This is a culmination of all the efforts you've put into the system.
And this is your greatest creation.
The architecture document describes the whole process you have been through and gives the developers
and management a full picture of the system that is going to be built.
A good architecture document is relevant for all the levels in the organization the CEO, the CIO,
the project manager, and of course, the developers.
They will all find great value in it.
We will talk a lot about the structure and the content of the document in the relevant section and explain
how to maximize its value.