The name factory might sound familiar, and it really is.
We already discussed factory methods in this course in previous lectures, mainly around layers.
But now let's do a real deep dive into the factory pattern and provide the full motivation and explanation
for it.
So what is a factory pattern?
Simply put, the factory pattern is a pattern that allows creating objects without specifying the exact
class of the object.
Now, why would we want to do that?
As we already discussed, specifying the class in the creating code will create a strong coupling and
will tie the code to the class.
If later, we will need to use another class for implementing the same logic, we will have to modify
all the code that creates the class which can be scattered all across the application.
So the factory pattern allows us to avoid such strong coupling.
How is it implemented?
Well, let's look at an example.
Say we have an application that needs to know the weather forecast in various cities around the world.
Now, there are multiple providers of weather forecasts and the developers decided to go with a provider
name, hot or not.
Whether they created a class called Hon or hon weather with a method named get weather that accepts
the city name and the date.
The get weather method returns a number which represents the temperature in the given city on the given
date.
Here is an example of a code using this class.
This is a straightforward implementation and it looks quite innocent.
Six months after the site went on production, the hugely successful hot or not weather went out of
business and the developers had to find a replacement.
After a hurried search, they found one named either neither weather.
They created another class named N weather with the same method signature get weather that accepts the
same arguments city and date and returned the same value the temperature.
Now what?
Now since the previous class on weather was directly created by the code using the new keyword, the
team has to find all the places this class is used and change the code to create an instance of the
weather class instead of the hon.
Weather Class.
This is a tedious, boring and error prone job.
What the team found out is that new is glue.
This is a common thing among developers and architects, and it shows that whenever we use the new keyword,
we glue the code and the class together.
The factory pattern proposes a solution for this.
Using the factory pattern.
We would do this create an interface named weather provider.
This interface has a single method named, you guessed it get weather accepting the city name and date
and returning the temperature to make the weather and n weather class implements this interface.
Create a factory method.
Let's call this method get weather provider and it will return an implementation of the weather provider
interface.
This method will simply return an instance of the weather.
That's all a one liner, but this one line changes everything.
From now on when the code needed to access weather information instead of calling directly to weather
it will cause a factory method, gets the instance and act on it.
The code will have no idea what is a concrete class it's using, and that makes the change a very easy
experience when the developers will need to switch from weather to weather.
All they need to do is to modify the code in the factory method.
That's it.
See how easy it is?
Using the factory method will definitely make your code easier to maintain, which is one of the major
goals of the architect.
Now there are some more complicated types of factory methods.
For example, let's say we have two weather providers, one for Asia and one for Europe.
We need the code to be indifferent to the location we want the weather forecast for.
And so we use the factory method as a place to make a decision about which instance to return.
For example, our weather classes are called, surprisingly enough, Europe Weather and Asia Weather,
and they both implement the weather provider interface.
Our factory will now look like this.
As you can see, the factory method accepts the continent name of the required weather forecast and
returns a different instance based on it.
This is a quite common pattern in factories and there are a lot of examples of factories making a decision
on a specific instance to be returned.
Another common pattern is to use an external configuration file for deciding which instance to return.
So that is a factory pattern.
And as you probably already understood, it is hugely popular and rightly so.
It will make your life much easier and the code will be more readable, flexible and easy to maintain.
In addition, the factory pattern is often a base for other patterns, as we will see in the repository
pattern.
So the bottom line is simple.
Always strive to use the factory pattern.
Remember new is glue.
Avoid strong coupling with the factory pattern.