The repository pattern is also one of the most known and widely used pattern, and it blends well into
a well-designed, layered architecture.
The repository pattern states that the modules not handling the actual work with the data store should
be completely oblivious to the data store type.
It's querying language, connection and transaction handling.
ET.
For example, if the data store is a MySQL database, no SQL statement should be issued by code module.
That is not part of the data handling code.
In other words, the repository pattern describes a data abstraction technique that should be used in
order to achieve the isolation we mentioned.
Now, that might sound familiar, as this definition is quite similar to the data access layer we discussed
in the layered architecture lecture.
And it's no coincidence both the repository pattern and the layered architectural pattern stems from
the same principles.
Making our software more flexible and easy to maintain.
The main difference between them is with their audience.
The layered architecture pattern is used mainly by architects, and design patterns are geared more
towards developers.
Nevertheless, as an architect, you will hear a lot about the repository pattern and you should definitely
know what all the fuss is about.
So back to the repository pattern.
We say this pattern provides abstraction layer above the data store.
How exactly does it do that?
Again, let's start with an example.
Our application manages the human resource department of the company.
The application needs to access the data store for the traditional Crud operations, create, read,
update and delete.
Now for the read operation, there are two requirements We need to retrieve an employee by her ID and
also to retrieve a list of employees by department name.
In a naive system, the developers create a method that handles all the data access.
This method is called by the UI or the service interface and does all the low level stuff of working
with the database.
In our example up the database is SQL Server, so the method issues standard SQL statements.
As you can see, the first method the developers created is a method for adding vacation days to a specific
employee.
Now, naturally, there is more than one place where the app needs to retrieve employees data so the
developers create more and more methods.
All of them issues SQL statements directly to the database, basically doing the same, which is retrieve
employee data.
The system goes on to production and everyone is happy.
Three months later, disaster strikes.
It appears a column name has to be changed.
Not a big change, just a typo that needs to be fixed.
Now, what is the effect of this tiny change in the current implementation?
The developers have to sift through all the methods in the app, find all the places where the original
name is used, and switch to the new one.
This is a tedious, boring, error prone task which will force the developers to modify a large chunk
of the code, which in turn will force the team to run all the tests again.
The repository pattern comes to the rescue in this case.
Using the repository pattern, these methods will never communicate directly with the database.
Instead, it will call a factory method, which you should be familiar with now, and get an instance
of the repository.
The repository represents the data store and exposes the actions the application requires.
For example, our repository represented by an interface called I Employees repository exposes the following
methods.
Get employee by ID.
Get employees by department.
Update Employee.
Create Employee and delete employee.
The factory method initializes a repository class, in this case a class that works against SQL Server
and issues the correct SQL statements and use it for the various methods.
The calling code has no idea what's going on in the repository class.
The data may be stored in a database in a file sent to other systems.
It simply doesn't care what will happen now when a single column is changed.
Simply only the repository class will be modified.
No other code should be touched.
This makes the change much more simple and focused, which makes it flexible and much, much easier
to maintain.
And consider another, more extreme case What will happen if a decision is made to switch to another
type of data store, say, from SQL Server to MongoDB?
In this case, the effect of the change in a non repository system will be huge.
The SQL statements should be rewritten, the connection mechanisms should be changed.
Transactions are a completely different beast.
It's virtually a full rewrite of the whole system.
But with the repository pattern, the change is subtler.
We simply create a new class implementing the I Employees repository interface point the factory method
to the new class and call it a day.
The other classes will not even know something has changed and that is the real strength of the repository
pattern.
Now this is the most basic form of the repository pattern.
There are more advanced forms that include.
Generic classes and inheritance and provide a better framework for extending the functionality.
But even in its most basic form, the repository pattern is one of the most useful pattern you will
ever use.