The facade pattern is one of the simplest patterns and still one of the most important of them.
In this pattern, a layer of abstraction is created in order to mask complex actions that lies underneath
it, thus helping the client to perform this action.
Again, let's explain it with an example.
Say we have a banking system.
Naturally, we need to have a way to transfer money between accounts.
The developers analyze the transfer process and comes up with a list of actions that should be performed.
One.
Make sure the accounts participating in the transfer actually exist.
To make sure there is enough money in the first account to perform the transfer.
Three.
Withdraw the money from the first account.
Four.
Deposit the money in the second account.
And five.
Add event in the account log documenting the transfer for both the accounts.
Now, being the pedantic developer they are, they build these five actions as five separate methods
in the code, which is good because all of these actions can stand on their own.
For example, we might need to make a check for funds on a specific account even when not transferring
money.
As a result of this, though, if a client now wants to transfer money, he has to access five methods.
It's a long and error prone process.
It's easy to forget one method or use the wrong parameters.
In short, a lot can go wrong here.
The facade pattern comes to the rescue.
The developers implement a facade which stands in front of the specific method and exposes a specific
focus functionality.
In our case, the facade is a method named transfer money, which accepts three arguments, account
to withdraw, account to deposit and some behind the scenes.
This method uses the above mentioned five methods to perform the transfer and not using any specific
code written for the method itself.
In other words, the facade does not invent new functionality.
It simply packages an existing one into an easy to use method.
Using the facade pattern makes your code much more readable and easy to use and is highly recommended.