The last pattern we will discuss is a command pattern.
The command pattern is less popular than the other patterns we discussed, but there are cases where
using it can really help make our code more flexible and easier to maintain.
Basically, the command pattern is a pattern in which all the action's information is encapsulated within
an object, including the action name parameters and the object on which the action is executed.
I know it sounds a bit complicated and as usual, let's explain it with an example.
Let's say we develop an undo mechanism.
I guess you know what it means.
But in case not.
Think of Microsoft Word, for example, where using the control Z keys, you can undo any actions you
performed and return to a previous state of the document.
This is definitely one of the most useful features of any software and writers as well as developers
appreciate and use a lot.
Now let's think how this mechanism can be implemented.
The undo mechanism should be able to perform a huge amount of actions deleting characters, changing
fonts, removing pages from the document and hundreds more.
In a naive implementation, the undo mechanisms code will include methods.
For all these actions.
It will look something like this.
As you can guess, this is not a good design.
This design actually mirrors all the functionality of the word processor and almost doubles its code.
In addition, when a new functionality is added to the software, a new code must be added to the undo
mechanism.
This will result in a huge code base which is difficult to maintain and is not really readable.
The command pattern that comes to the rescue in the case using this pattern.
The undo mechanism simply holds a list of commands to execute.
It has no idea what those commands do.
It only knows each command has a method named execute that will do whatever is needed, so the implementation
now will look like this.
First, we define an interface.
Let's call it I command.
This interface contains a single method execute.
Next, we will define various classes, represent commands that should be executed.
For example delete word.
These classes implement the interface.
These classes hold all the needed information required to execute the command.
For example, in a class that deletes a word, we probably need a reference to the document containing
the word and the word that needs to be deleted in it.
Of course, in real life, the implementation will be much more complicated with reference to the console's
location and more.
But for the sake of simplicity, I'll keep it this way.
Now the class should actually perform the deletion.
For that we will create a method called delete which will do just that.
The actual implementation is not very important, but suffice to say such method exists.
Last the interface implementation.
Remember this class implements the I command interface and therefore has to implement the execute method.
This method simply calls the delete method in the command pattern.
This class is called the command object and the document we are working on is called the Receiver.
Now let's go back to the undo mechanism.
This mechanism holds a queue of commands for any action performed on the document.
A new command object is added to the queue.
When an undo is requested, the undo mechanism simply pops a command from the queue and calls it execute
method in the command pattern.
The undo mechanism is a invoker.
It invokes the execute method.
Note that in no point has the undo mechanism any idea what the actual command is.
All it knows is that there is a command object with an execute method that takes care of a specific
undo action and that is the beauty of the command pattern.
The complete separation between the invocation of the command and its actual function.
The invoker has no idea what the command does.
All it knows is that it should be invoked.
All the components required for the command execution are stored within the command object.
As we said before, the command pattern is less popular than the other patterns we discussed.
But when it is relevant, it will make your life and the code much easier.