In this section, we discuss the design patterns we talked about for patterns, factory repository,
facade and command.
These patterns, when implemented correctly, will help you design software which is more consistent,
flexible, readable and easy to maintain.
On the other hand, don't rush to implement all the patterns exist.
One of the mistakes junior architects do is designing a patterns oriented architecture, which is an
architecture that tries to implement as many patterns as possible instead of keeping things simple.
So don't do that either, and use only the patterns you really need in the resource document attached
to this lecture.
There are some resources for learning more about the various design patterns and I highly recommend
going through them.
I hope this section helped you understand the basics of design patterns and I hope you will find a real
value using them.