Wow.
We did it.
We've just reached the end of a very long journey.
You began this journey as a developer or system analyst or team leader, and you end it as an architect.
Congratulations.
Let's have a quick review of what we learned in this course.
After a brief introduction in which we talked about reasons to be an architect, we asked, What is
a software architect?
We talked about three types of architects.
Infrastructure architect.
Software Architect and enterprise architect.
We also talked about the architect in the organizational tree and that she should be able to code.
In the next section, we discussed the architect's mindset.
We emphasized an architect must be business oriented and make sure the architecture contributes to the
bottom line of the business.
Then we talked about the architecture process and outlined the various steps that an architect should
take in order to make sure the architecture is sound and successful.
We then explored the system requirements and discussed the difference between functional and non-functional
requirements.
After the requirements, we looked at a list of the various application types and determined which type
is the best fit for each scenario.
Having selected the application type, we looked at technology stack and discussed the various technologies
that are candidates for back end, front end mobile and desktop apps, as well as the difference between
relational databases and NoSQL databases.
We concluded by emphasizing this decision must be made rationally.
Since this topic is often quite loaded, we then met a family of quality attributes called Collectively
The Star Highlights.
We talked about scalability, manageability, modularity, extensibility and testability and explained
their importance in the overall architecture.
And then we started to discuss architecture.
We first talked about components architecture, explained what a component is and how it should be designed.
We also talked about layered architecture, one of the most important concepts in the architecture world,
and one that will be used in almost every application you will design.
We then learned a little bit about design patterns, although these are relevant mainly to developers.
We talked about their importance to the architect.
Having concluded the component architecture, we turned our attention to the system architecture and
discussed concepts such as loose coupling, stateless caching, messaging and logging and monitoring.
We continued to the next section to discuss various external considerations you must be aware of, such
as deadlines and costs, and understood that ignoring them might render our architecture irrelevant.
And then we talked about the architecture document, probably the most important aspect of the architect's
work.
This document summarizes all the architecture process and provides the team with comprehensive guidance
about their system.
And then we put it all to a practical test and discussed a real world case study of an Iot company that
needs a new system.
We went through all the steps discussed earlier and saw how to utilize them in practice.
The result of this exercise was a real practical architecture document that you can freely use in your
own systems.
Next, we discussed some advanced architecture topics such as event sourcing and microservices.
You won't necessarily use them, but it's a good idea to be familiar with them.
And last we learned about some soft skills architects have to have.
We discussed listening, dealing with criticism, public speaking and more.
All of these skills will make us all better architects and basically better persons.
And here we are at the end of it all.
I hope you had a great time in this course and I hope you've learned a lot.
I hope you feel ready for the next challenge and that you have all the tools you need to become a great
architect.
As always, do not hesitate to contact me with every question or comment you have.
I love to hear from my students and I promise to get back to you.
Thanks for being with me in this course and good luck in your new life as a software architect.